In the last lecture we learned about in
sample
and out of sample errors as well as over
fitting.
In this lecture we'll talk about
prediction study design or how to minimize
the problems that can be caused by in
sample verses out of sample errors.
So in prediction study design the first
thing that
we need to do is to find our error rate.
So in this lecture we're just going to use
a generic error rate, but in the
next lecture we'll talk about what are
the different possible error rates you can
choose.
Then you need to split your data, the data
that you're going to be using
to build and validate your model into
three
components, well, two components and one
optional component.
So there's a training set that must be
created
in order to build your model, a testing
set to
evaluate your model, and optionally a
validation set as well,
which is also going to be used to validate
your model.
So what you do is on the training
set, you pick features using
cross-validation, for example.
We'll talk about what cross-validation is
later in
the course, but the idea is basically to
use that training set to pick which of
the features that are most important in
your model.
Then use that same technique to actually
pick the prediction function
and estimate all the parameters that you
might be interested in.
We build a model using the training set.
If there's no validation set, then we
apply the best
model that we have to our test set exactly
one time.
And so the, why do we only apply it one
time?
If we applied multiple models to our
testing set, then, and pick the best
one, then we're using the test set, in
some sense, to train the model.
In other words, we're still getting an
optimistic view of
what the data error would be on a
completely new dataset.
So you should apply the prediction model
to the test set exactly one time.
If there's a validation set and a test set
then you might apply your
best prediction models all to your test
set and refine them a little bit.
So what you might find is that some
features don't work so well when you're
doing out of sample prediction and you
might
refine and adjust your model a little bit.
But now, again, like I said, your test set
error is going to be
a little bit optimistic error for what
your actual out of sample error will be.
And so what we do is we again, apply our
model to exactly
one time to the validation set, only the
best one to get our prediction.
So in other words, the idea is that there
is one dataset that's
held out from the very start, that you
only apply exactly one model
to, and you never do any training or
tuning or testing to, and
that will give you a good estimate of your
out of sample error rates.
So an important point to keep in mind when
you doing this is to know what the
benchmarks are.
So this is an example of a leaderboard
from a [UNKNOWN] competition.
And so they often give you benchmarks,
marking grey here on this plot
that shows what happens if you say make
all the values equal to 0.
And it's a good idea to know
what the prediction benchmark are because
sometimes if
you prediction algorithm is performing way
better than it should be or way worse than
it should be, the benchmarks will give you
some idea of what you should be
doing wrong, and they'll tell you if
your prediction algorithm is kind of going
astray.
So this is the studied design that was
used in the Netflix prize, so they had
a 100 million ident-user-ident pairs, in
other words,
movies that people had given their
preference on.
They split that into a training data set,
which they were going
to give to, users that we're going to
build models for prediction.
Then, they held out, a bunch of ratings
that we're not going
to be shown at all to the people that are
building the models.
And so, what they provided for people who
were building motels,
was a training set, and what they called a
probe data set.
So, you would train your model on the
training data
set and then you would apply it to the
probe
data set to get some idea of what the out
of sample error would be, before
submitting it to Netflix.
Then what Netflix would do is they would
take your
predictions and they would apply it only
to a quiz set.
So this quiz set you didn't get at get to
actually see, and you couldn't build your
model on, but if we give you some better
idea of how well your model would perform
at
a sample, but in general people could
submit multiple
submissions to this quiz set and so they
might
actually tune their models a little bit
and get
a little bit better performance on the
quiz set.
And so what they did ultimately was for
the
final evaluation of all the different
teams, they applied the
model just one time to this test set that
was held out to the very end of the
competition.
And so at the very end of the competition
they got an unbiased estimate of how well
this model
would work on a completely new set of data
that
the participants in the competition never
had a look at.
So this idea was actually very important
in their study design and it
actually turned out that some teams that
did better on the quiz set, actually
didn't do quite as well on the test set
and that was because they
were tuning in their models or over
fitting their models to the quiz set.
So this is an important take home message
for
you, in the sense that if you're building
prediction
models, you always have to hold one data
set,
and leave it completely aside while you're
building your models.
This is now used by group professionals so
Kaggle is a company that actually runs
lots
of co, competitions for prediction
competitions for a
whole bunch of different data sets
provided by companies.
And they always do a similar model in the
sense that they always have a leader board
that consists of the predictions that
people have
submitted for a validation data set that
they have.
But it's not necessarily the data set that
they'll
use to validate their methods at the very
end.
That data set is held out until the very
end, and each
person gets to apply their algorithm to
that data set only one time.
Something to keep in mind is that when
you're splitting your
data sets up into training, testing and
validation sets, they can
get a little bit small, but you need to
avoid small
sample sizes, particularly if you're
dealing with the test set size.
And the reason why is, suppose you were
predicting a binary outcome, so in my
case, a very common thing to try to do is
to predict diseased versus healthy.
And in general, it might be something
like, whether people will
click on an ad, or whether they won't
click on an ad.
Then one classifier is just flipping a
coin.
You could always just flip a coin, and
say, they'll be diseased if
the coin is heads, and not diseased if the
coin comes out tails.
And so the probability of a perfect
classification, using this
really silly algorithm is one half raised
to the sample size.
In other words, half the time you'll be
right, just by chance by flipping the
coin.
And each time, supposing each prediction
is independent,
then each time that you flip a coin, then
you'll get one half times that, a number
will
be the decrease in accuracy that you would
get.
So if you were pr-, test set has only one
sample in
it, then you have about a 50/50 chance of
getting that sample right.
So, even if you got prediction accuracy of
100% on the test set,
you would have a 50% chance of that, even
with a coin flip.
With n equals 2, you only have a, you
still only have a 25% chance of 100%
accuracy.
And with n equals 10 in your test set, now
you have, only about a .1% chance of
getting 100% accuracy.
So if you see that 100% accuracy you'll
feel a little bit
more confident that it's actually true and
it's not something that's just random.
So this suggests that we should make sure
that especially our test sizes are of
relatively
large size so we can be sure that
we're not just getting good prediction
accuracy by chance.
So some rules of thumb, these are by
no means set in stone, but they are
reasonable
rules of thumb that I've used and I think
a lot of people have used similar ones.
So you set, when you get a new data set,
if it's large enough, you'll set 60% of
your data set
to be training, 20% of your data set to be
test, and 20% of your valid, data set to
be validation.
This is again assuming that your test and
validation
data sets won't be too small if you do
that.
If you have a medium sample size what you
might do is you might take 60%
of your data set to be training and 40% of
your data set to be testing.
This means you don't get to refine your
models in
a test set and then apply them to a
validation set.
But it might insure that your testing site
is of sufficient size.
Finally, if you have a very small sample
size.
First of all, you might reconsider whether
you have enough samples
to be able to build a prediction algorithm
in the first place.
But suppose your dead set on building a
prediction or machine learning
algorithm, then the idea might be to do
cross validation and report the
caveat of the small sample size and the
fact that you never got
to predict this in an out of sample or a
testing data set.
So
some principles to remember are the test
set or the validation set
should be set aside and never looked at
when building your model.
In other words, you would need to have one
data set which you apply only one model
to, only
one time, and that data set should be
completely
independent of anything you use to build
the prediction model.
In general you want to randomly sample the
training and test set and
random might depend on the type of
sampling that you want to do.
So for example, if you have, time fit time
force
data, in other words you have, data
collected over time, you
might want to build your, training set in
chunks of time, but
again, random chunks of time and build
them on random predictions.
Your data set much reflect the structure
of the problem.
In other words, if you want to sample any
data set that might have sources
of dependence over time or across space,
you need to sample your data in chunks.
This is called backtesting in finance.
And it's basically the idea that you want
to be able
to use chunks of data that consist of
observations over time.
All subsets should re, reflect as much
diversity as possible.
If you do random assignment, it does this.
You might also try balancing by features.
This can be a little bit tricky, but it
often is a useful idea.