This lecture is about the types of errors
and the ways that
you will evaluate the prediction functions
that you generate during this class.
So, first of all we're going to focus on,
the types of
errors that you can make when you're doing
a binary prediction problem.
In other words, you were trying to predict
things into one of two groups.
In general, we're going to be talking
about langauge in terms of
true positives and true negatives, and
false positives and false negatives.
So the first thing to keep in mind is
that, when we
talk about positive versus negative, we're
actually talking about what the algorithm
decided.
Whether it decided that you're in a class,
or not in a class.
Then true and false, refer to the true
state of the world.
So, true means that you actually belong to
the class we're trying
to identify, and false means that you
actually don't belong to that class.
So as an example, true positive mean, the
true part of true positive, means that you
were correctly, so in other words that,
the
truth is that there actually was something
to identify.
A positive.
In other words, we actually identified you
as being belonging to that class.
Similarly for a false positive, the
positive part
again refers to the fact that we
identified you
as being part of the positive class, and
false refers to the fact that you were
wrong.
We didn't actually corr, classify you to
the correct class.
To make this a little more concrete,
consider a medical testing example.
So in this case, we're trying to identify
people that are sick using say a screening
test,
a very common example would be, say
mammograms
to try to identify if women have breast
cancer.
In this case, the true part will be the
status as to whether you're sick or not.
So if we say that we truly identified you,
then you were truly sick.
And if we falsely identified you, then you
were actually healthy.
You were not truly sick.
So in this case, a true positive, is
truly, somebody who is truly sick.
And it's positive, in other words, we
actually
diagnosed those people as correctly as
being sick.
If you're a false positive it means that,
false, in other words you are a healthy
person,
but positive, means that we were still
somebody that
we identified as being sick, even though
you weren't.
Similarly with a true negative.
This is somebody true, who is truly
negative,
truly healthy, and we identified them as
being negative.
And a false negative would be somebody who
is sick, so we incorrectly identified
them as healthy, and the negative part of
is we identified them as healthy.
You can learn more about sensitivity and
specificity by going to this Wikipedia
link below.
You can also see them in this 2 by 2
table.
So it's called a 2 by 2 table, because it
has two rows, here, and two columns, here.
So, the columns correspond to what your
disease status is.
So, in this, in this particular example,
positive means that you
have the disease, and negative means that
you don't have the disease.
That's the real truth about your disease
status.
And the test is our prediction, our
machine learning algorithm.
A positive means we predict that you have
a disease and
a negative means that we predict that you
don't have the disease.
So some of the key quantities that people
talk about, are the sensitivity.
This is the probability that we give you
a, predict that you are diseased, given
that
you really are diseased, so, if you're
really
diseased, what's the probability we get
that, right?
And then the specificity is if you are
really healthy, what's the probability we
get it right?
The positive predictive value is the
probability that we call you diseased,
or the probability that you are diseased,
given that we call you diseased.
So it's a little bit different, than the
sensitivity in the sense that, now it's
looking at all the people we called
po diseased, and saying, what fraction of
them.
Actually are diseased.
Similarly for the negative predictive
value.
And the accuracy is just a probability
that we classified you to the correct
outcome.
So in this table, it's the terms on the
diagonal.
It's the true positives, and the true
negatives, just added up.
So you can write these as fractions.
So for example, the sensitivity.
That's the probability, given that you are
diseased, that we called you diseased.
So we look at this first column.
This is all the people that are diseased.
And we look, what fraction of them, did we
actually get right.
So that's, the true positives, divided by
the true
positives, plus the false negatives, that
gives you the sensitivity.
You can similarly make the same sort of
fractions for the
specificity, the positive predictive
value, the
negative predictive value, and so forth.
When looking at the positive predictive
value.
We basically look at the, in this case
it's the
true positives, divided by the true
positives plus the false positives,
because we're looking at only the positive
tests, and we
say what fraction of the positive tests
did we get right?
So the true positives were the ones that
we got right, and the
true positives plus the false positives,
is the total of the positive tests.
So this is kind of important because, many
prediction problems,
one of the classes will be more rare than
the other.
So, for example in, in medical studies,
it's very common
that only a very small percentage of
people will be sick.
In this case, suppose that there's a
disease where only
one, 0.1% of the people are sick in the
population.
And suppose we have a really good machine
learning algorithm.
A really good testing kit, that is 99%
sensitive, and 99% specific.
In other words, the probability that we'll
get it right, if you're diseased
is 99%, and the probability we'll get it
right if you're healthy is 99%.
So in this case, suppose that you get a
positive test.
What's the probability, that we'll, that
you actually have the disease?
You can consider two different cases.
One, in a general population.
In other words, in a population where
there's
a very small chance that you have the
disease.
Another one you can consider, is a case
where 10% of
people have the disease, so the disease is
much more prevalent.
Let's look at how that changes your
positive predictive value.
So the general population, remember, we
only have
about 1% of the people that have the
disease.
So there are only 100 people in this
column, that have the
disease, sim, but there are a lot more
people that are healthy.
Similarly, we have a 99% accuracy, if you
have the disease.
So, 99 out of 100 people.
And 99 out of these 100, are correctly
called diseased.
Similarly, at, among the people that are
healthy, we get 99%
right, so 98,901 we call healthy, when
they really are healthy.
That's 99% of the time.
But suppose that we wanted to know, if you
got a
positive test, what's the probability that
you actually have the disease?
So, let's look at this for a second.
So you say.
Suppose you actually got a positive test,
that's this first row right here.
What's the probability that you actually
have the disease?
So that's, the number of people that
actually have the disease, among
the total number of people who had a
positive test, so that's 99.
Divided by 99 plus 999, so it's only a 9%
positive predictive value.
In other words, if you got a positive te,
test, it's
only about a 9% chance that you actually
have the disease.
What's the reason for that?
The reason is 99% of a small number, so 99
out of 100.
Is still smaller than 1% out of a much
bigger number.
So 999 out of a much larger fraction that
are actually healthy people.
If instead we consider the case where 10%
of people are actually sick,
then you have a much larger number of
people that are actually sick.
And 99% of the time, we'll get it right,
so 99, 9,900 of people, that actually are
sick, we'll call sick, and only 900 of
the people that are healthy will be called
sick.
And so then, things work out how you'd
expect them to.
In other words, 9,900 out of 9,900 plus
900, so that's.
This number on the top left-hand corner.
Divided by this total row.
Is 92%, and so you have a high positive
predictive value.
What does this mean?
If you're predicting a rare event.
You have to be aware of, how rare that
event is.
This goes back to the idea of knowing what
population you're sampling from.
When you're building the a predictive
model.
This is actually a key public health
issue, so you've probably
seen it in the news that there's been
questions about how,
what's the value of mammograms in
detecting disease, and detecting the
value of disease versus detecting cases
that aren't necessarily life threatening.
Similarly, you've probably heard about it
for prostate
cancer screening, and in both of these
cases.
You have a fairly rare disease, and even
though the
screening mechanisms are relatively good,
it's very hard to know whether
you're getting a lot of false positives
that are, as
a fraction of the total number of
positives that you're getting.
For continuous data, you actually don't
have quite
so simple a scenario, where you only have
one of two cases, and one of two types of
errors that you can possibly make.
The goal here is to see how close you are
to the truth.
And so, one common way to do that, is with
something called mean squared error.
And so the idea is, you have a prediction
that
you have from your model or your machine
learning algorithm.
And so, you have a prediction for
every single sample that you're trying to
predict.
And you also maybe know the truth for
those samples, say in a test set.
So what you do is, you calculate
the difference between the prediction and
the truth.
And you square it, so the numbers are all
positive.
And then you average the total number of,
sort
of total distance between the pre,
prediction and the tree.
The one thing that's a little bit
difficult about
interpreting this number is that you
squared this distance,
and so, it's a little bit hard to
interpret
on the same scale as the predictions or
the truth.
And so what people often do is they take
the square root of that quantity.
So here, underneath the square root sign,
is the same number, it's just the average
distance between the prediction and the
truth, and you just sum it and square it.
And then you take the square root in that
number,
and that gives you the root, root mean
squared error.
And this is probably the most common error
measure that's used for continuous data.
So for continuous data, people often use
either
the mean squared error, or the mean
squared error.
But if often doesn't work when there are a
lot of outliers.
Or the values of the variables can have
very different scales.
Because, it will be sensitive to those
outliers.
So, for example, if you have one really,
really large value.
It might really raise the mean.
Instead, what we could use is often the
median absolute deviation.
So in that case, they take the median
of the diff, distance between the observed
value,
and the predicted value, and they do the
absolute value instead of doing the
squared value.
And so again, that requires all of the
distances to be positive,
but it's a little bit more robust to the
size of those errors.
And then sensitivity and spe specificity
are very commonly
used when talking about particularly
medical tests, but they also
are particularly widely used if you care
about one
type of error more than the other type of
error.
And then, accuracy which weights false
positives and false positives equally.
This is an important point if again you
have a very large.
Discrepancy in number of times that you're
a positive or a negative.
For multiclass cases, you might have
something like concordance,
and here I've linked to one particular
distance measure, kappa.
But there are a whole large class of
distance measures, and they
all have different properties, that can be
used when you have multiclass data.
So, those are some of the common error
measures that are used when doing
prediction algorithms.