A lot of the action in machine learning
has focused on what
algorithms are the best algorithms for
extracting information and using it to
predict.
But it's important to step back and look
at the entire prediction problem.
This is a little diagram that I made to
illustrate
some of the key each, issues in building a
predictor.
So you start of with, suppose I want to
predict for these dots whether they're red
or blue.
Well, what you might do is have a big
group of dots that you
want to predict about, and then you use
probability and sampling to pick a
training set.
The training set will consist of some red
dots and some blue
dots, and you'll measure a whole bunch of
characteristics of those dots.
Then you'll use those characteristics to
build what's called a
prediction function, and the prediction
function will take a new dot,
whose color you don't know, but using
those characteristics that
you measured will predict whether it's red
or whether it's blue.
Then you can go off and try to
evaluate whether that prediction function
works well or not.
One thing that I think is very important
and often underappreciated about building
a machine learning
algorithm is to look at probability and
sampling
step of building the training and test
stats.
This is always a required component of
building every machine learning algorithm
is deciding which samples you're going to
use to build that algorithm.
But sometimes it's over-looked, because
all of the action that you hear about for
machine learning happens down here when
you're
building the actual machine learning
function itself.
One very high profile example of the ways
that this
can cause problems is the recent
discussion about Google Flu trends.
Google Flu trend is tried to use the terms
that people were typing into
Google, terms like, I have a cough, to
predict how often people would get flu.
In other words, what was the rate of flu
that was going
on in a particular part of the United
States at a particular time?
And they compared their algorithm to
approach taken
by the United States government, where
they went out
and they actually measured how many people
were
getting the flu, in different places in
the US.
And they found in their original paper
that the
Google Flu trends algorithm was able to
very accurately represent
the number of flu cases that would appear
in
various different places in the US at any
given time.
But it was quite a bit faster and quite a
bit less expensive to measure using search
terms at Google.
The problem that they didn't realize at
the time, was that
the search terms that people would use
would change over time.
They might use different terms when they
were
searching, and so that would affect the
algorithm's performance.
And also, the way that those terms were
actually
being used in the algorithm wasn't very
well understood.
And so when the function of a particular
search
term changed in their algorithm, it can
cause problems.
And this lead to highly inaccurate results
for the Google
Flu trends algorithm half over time as
people's internet usage changes.
So this gives you an idea that choosing
the right dataset and that knowing what
the specific
question is are again paramount, just like
they have
been in other classes of the data science
specialization.
So here are the components of a predictor.
You need to start off as always in all,
any problem
with data science with a very specific and
well defined question.
What are you trying to predict and what
are you trying to predict it with?
Then you go out and you collect the best
input data that you can to be able to
predict.
And from that data you might either use
measured
characteristics that you have or you might
use computations
to build features that we'd think you
might be
useful for predicting the outcome that you
care about.
At this stage then you can actually start
to use the machine learning
algorithms you may have read about, such
as Random Forest or Decision Trees.
And then what you can do is estimate the
parameters of those algorithms, and use
those parameters to
apply the algorithm to a new data set and
then finally evaluate that algorithm on
that new data.
So I'm going to just show you one quick
little
example, to show you how this little
process works.
So this is obviously a trivialized version
of what would happen in a
real machine running algorithm, but it
gives you a flavor of what's going on.
So you start off with asking something
about the question.
So you start with a in general
people usually start with a quite general
questions.
So here is, can I automatically detect
emails
that are SPAM from those that are not?
So SPAM emails are emails that you got
that you, come from companies that get
sent out
to thousands of people at the same time
and that you might not be interested in
it.
So you might want to make your question a
little bit more concrete.
You often need to when doing machine
learning.
So, the question might be, can I use
quantitative characteristics of those
emails to classify them as
SPAM, or what we're going to call HAM
which
is the email that people would like to
receive?
So once you have your question, then you
need to find input data.
In this case, there's actually a bunch of
data
that's available and already pre-processed
for us in R.
So it's actually in the current lab
package K-E-R-N-L-A-B and it's the SPAM
dataset.
So we can actually load that data set into
R directly, and it has some information
that's been collected about SPAM and HAM
emails already available to us.
Now we might want to keep in mind that
that might
not necessarily be the perfect data, in
fact, we don't have all
of the emails that have been collected
over time, or we
don't have all the emails that are being
sent to you personally.
So we need to be aware of the potential
limitations of this
data, when we're using it to build an
algorithm, a prediction algorithm.
Then we want to calculate something about
features.
So, imagine that you have a bunch of
emails.
And here's an example email that's been
sent to me.
Dear Jeff, can you send me the address, so
I can send you the invitation.
Thanks, Ben.
If we want to build a prediction
algorithm,
we need to calculate some characteristics
of
these emails that we can use to be able to
build a predictive algorithm.
And so one example might be, we can
calculate the frequency with which a
particular word appears.
So here, we're looking for the frequency
that the word you appears.
And so in this case, it appears twice in
this email so 2 out
of 17 words or about 11% of the words in
this email are you.
We could calculate that same percentage
for every single email that we have and
now we have a qualitative characteristic
that we can try to use to predict.
So if the data in the current lab package
that I've shown here are actually,
information just like that, for every
email we
have the frequency with which certain
words appear.
And so, for example if credit appears very
often in the email or money appears
very often in the email, you might imagine
that that email might be a SPAM email.
So, as one example of that, we looked at
the frequency
of the word, your, and how often it
appears in the email.
And so, I've got a plot here that's a
density plot of the, that data.
And so, on the x-axis is the frequency
that with which, your, appeared in the
email.
And on the y-axis is the density, or the
number of times the that frequency appears
amongst the emails.
And so what you can see is that most of
the emails that are SPAM, those are the
ones that are in red, you can see that
they tend to have more appearances of the
word, your.
Where as all of the emails that are HAM,
the
ones that we actually want to receive have
a much higher peak
right over here down near 0, so there's
very few
emails that have a large number of viewers
that are HAM.
So, we can build an algorithm in this case
let's build a very very simple algorithm.
We can estimate an algorithm where we want
to just find a cut off a constant C, where
if the frequency of your is above C then
we predict spam and otherwise we predict
that it's ham.
So going back to our data we can fig, try
to figure out what
that best cut off is, and here's an
example of a cutoff that you could
choose, so choose a cut off here that if
it's above 0.5 then we
say that it's SPAM, and if it's below 0.5
we can say that it's HAM.
And so we think this might work because
you can see that
the large spike of blue HAM messages are
below that cut off.
Whereas the big, one of the big spikes of
the SPAM messages is above that cut off.
So you might imagine that wil cache quite
a bit of that SPAM.
So then what we do is we evaluate that.
So what we would do is calculate for
example predictions for each of the
different emails.
We take a prediction in that says, if the
frequency of yours
above 0.5, then you're spam and if it's
below then you're nonspam.
And then we make a table of those
predictions and divide
it by the length of the, all the
observations that we have.
And so we can say is that, when you're
nonspam about
45% of the time, 46% of the time, we get
you right.
When you're spam about 29% of the time, we
get you right.
So, total we get you write about 45% plus
29% is about 75% of the time.
So our prediction algorithm is about 75%
accurate in this particular case.
So that's how we would evaluate the
algorithm.
This is of course any same dataset where
we actually calculated
it, the prediction function, and as we
will see in later lectures.
This will be an optimistic estimate of the
overall error rate.
So that's an overview of, the basic steps
in building a predictive algorithm.