This lecture's about the tradeoffs and the
different components of building a machine
learning algorithm.
So remember, from the previous lecture
that we talked
about the different components of building
a machine learning algorithm.
We started off with a question.
So this is the question we are trying to
answer,
and we try to make it as concrete as
possible.
Then we collect some data.
The data that we're going to be using to
build our
machine learning algorithm and to the,
apply that algorithm later on.
From that data we compress it into a set
of features that we're going to use to
predict with.
And then we feed those features into an
algorithm
which we'll then use to apply to predict
things.
In my experience, it's been that the
question
is the most important component of
building a
good machine learning algorithm, getting a
very concrete
and specific question where you can
collect data.
The next most important step is to be able
to actually collect data.
Frequently the question that you actually
really want to answer, the data won't
be available, or the data will be only
available in a sort of tangential.
Form.
Then creating features is an important
component
in that if you don't compress the
data in the right way you might lose all
of the relevant and valuable information.
And finally, in my experience it's been
the algorithm is
often the least important part of building
a machine learning algorithm.
It can be very important depending on the
exact
modality of the type of data that you're
using.
For example, image data and voice data can
require certain
kinds of prediction algorithms that might
not necessarily be as.
Important for different kinds of
prediction.
So an important point that I think is
worth hammering home is
driven was actually first quoted by John
Tukey, which is that the combination
of some data and and aching desire for an
answer does not ensure
that a reasonable answer can be extracted
from a given body of data.
In other words, an important component of
knowing how
to do prediction is to know when to give
up,
when the data that you have is just not
sufficient to answer the question that
you're trying to answer.
The key point that you need to remember.
When making that decision is garbage in
garbage out.
In other words if you have bad data that
you collected.
Or data that isn't very useful for
performing predictions.
No matter how good your machine learning
algorithm is.
You'll often get very bad results out.
In general the easiest thing to predict is
when you have
data on the exact same thing that you're
trying to predict.
In other words when you're.
In the Netflix prize they were trying to
predict new movie ratings, how people
would rate
movies and they were trying to make that
prediction on the basis of old movie
ratings.
And so that's a very direct relationship,
you
can imagine how old movie ratings would
be.
Governed by similar process as the new
movie ratings.
In my area one thing that you might do is
collect molecular measurements such as
gene expression and that's a that's a
measure
of something that's going on in your body.
And you might use that to try to predict
how people respond.
To disease or to other different medical
conditions.
Again they're sort of a, you can imagine a
pathway from the gene expression
data we've collected, the molecular
information we've
collected, a value to your disease status.
In general it depends, what is a good
prediction, what are
the features that you would collect to be
able to predict.
But in general the closer that you could
get to similar types of
data, the closer that you can do to
perform a high prediction of accuracy.
This is a link here to a video
that talks about the, unreasonable
effectiveness of data.
In other words, that getting a lot more
data can often beat
out getting much better statistical or
machine learning models in almost every
case.
And the most important step in developing
a machine learning
algorithm after you define a question is
collecting the right data.
Data that's relevant for the question
you're trying to answer.
The features also matter.
So the important properties of good
features are
that they compress the data in a way that
make it possible to compute your
prediction, or
your machine learning algorithm, in a very
simple way.
And maybe are more interpretable than the
data that
you've collected that's the raw data that
might be complicated.
They're, the good features retain all the
relevant information while compressing
the data, and that can be a hard balance
to strike.
They're also usually created with expert
application knowledge, and
this is something that there's a debate in
the
community about whether it's better to
create features automatically
or whether it's better to use expert
domain knowledge.
And in general it seems that the, expert
domain knowledge can help quite a bit in
many, many applications and so should be
consulted
when building a features for machine
learning algorithm.
Some common mistake are trying to automate
feature selection in a way
that doesn't allow for you to understand
how those features are actually.
Being applied to make good predictions.
Black box predictions can be very useful,
they
can be very accurate but they can also
change
on a dime if we're not paying attention
to how those features actually do predict
the outcome.
Not paying attention to data specific
quirks is another
problem that can come up so in some cases.
The function of a particular set of data
set might be that there's outlines
if there's weird behaviors of specific
features
and not understanding those can cause
problems.
And obviously throwing away information
unnecessarily is not a good idea.
You can automate feature selections
sometimes with care,
in fact there's a whole area of research
that's
been dedicated to this so what I would
call sort of semi supervised learning or
deep learning.
And so the idea in this paper was to try
to use, to try to discover features of
YouTube videos.
That could later be used in prediction
algorithms.
So for example they were able to create a
very accurate
predictor of whether you were a cat in a
video or not.
Based on a bunch of features they sort of
collected in an unsupervised way.
In other words they filtered through the
data in a way
to identify those features that might be
useful for later predictive algorithms.
But even when they did this, they went
back and looked
at those features and tried to figure out
why they would be
predictive and so for example these
features, this feature here makes it
very clear why it would be a good
predictor for a cat.
Because you can kind of see the image of a
cat there in the video.
Feature that they've collected.
Algorithms matter less than you'd think,
and this can be a
bit of a source of surprise and
frustration for some people.
So this is an, a table where they actually
tried predicting
a variety of different prediction tasks,
for example, sort of a
segmentation task, predicting votes in the
US House of Representatives, and
predicting wave forms, and a bunch of
other different prediction tasks.
And so they did it with two different
ways, first they used something called
linear discriminant analysis which is sort
of
a very basic early predictor you might
learn.
And then they also tried for each data
set to find the absolute best prediction
algorithm
they could have and then this table shows
the prediction error of these two
different approaches.
And you can see that the best prediction
error is
always a little bit better than the linear
discriminant error.
But, it's actually not that far off.
So, for example, here in this Pima
prediction, it was
0.19 was the, 0.197 was the error with the
best method.
And 0.22 for linear discriminate analysis.
So it seems like using the same method
over and over
again did make the prediction error worse,
but not incredibly worse.
And so that's very typical of many
applications.
That.
Using a very, sensible approach will get
you
a very large weight of solving the
problem.
And then, getting the absolute best method
can improve, but it
often doesn't improve that much over, sort
of, most good sensible methods.
Some issues to consider when building a
machine
learning algorithm are there, there's
different components to it.
First, it might, you might need it to be
interpretable.
In other words, if you're going to be
showing
this machine learning algorithm to doctors
or, in my case.
Or in the case of a web company you might
want to show this to the CEO.
You want your predictor to be
interpretable so they can understand it.
Part of being interpretable is often being
simple, in other words, being very
easy to explain is often better than being
really complicated and hard to understand.
And often you have trade offs with respect
to accuracy, so getting those
two qualities can reduce your accuracy,
and the question is how much do they.
Reduce your accuracy.
Is it too much to give up
the interpretability and the simplicity
that you gain?
You also want it to be scalable and fast.
By fast I mean it's very easy to, build
the
model, it's very easy to test the model in
small samples.
Scalable means it's easy to apply to a
large data set.
Whether that's because it's very very fast
or whether
it's because it's parallelizable across
multiple samples for example.
So in the general prediction it's about
accuracy tradeoffs.
So the idea is sometimes you will trade
off a
lot of accuracy or a little bit of
accuracy for interpretability.
Sometimes you'll trade it off for speed or
simplicity or scalability.
But in general, what you're trying to do
is
find that right balance between those,
those other features
of the prediction algorithm that might be
important to
you, and how accurate you need it to be.
Interpretability often matters, so for
example, in medical
studies, this is a paper that studied how
some
physicians like better prediction rules
that look like
this, they look a little bit like decision
trees.
In other words.
You start off and you say if total
cholesterol is above
a particular value and you smoke, then you
get a certain outcome.
So those sort of if/then statements can be
very interpretable to some people,
and so that's about the reason why people
like things like decision trees.
And that can matter more or less depending
on what your, the purpose of your
algorithm is.
But interpretablity prevents things like
the
Google flu trends problem where people
didn't
really understand how the features were
directly tied to the rate of flu.
And so if you don't understand how the
features are working, you
can get caught when the algorithm starts
to, have problems or fail.
Scalability also matters.
A very interesting component of this
Netflix challenge is that
the Netflix prize was a million dollar
challenge, and they
had lots of teams compete, and several
teams produced analytic
algorithms that were much better
at predicting than Netflix original
algorithm.
But it turns out they actually never
implemented the
final algorithm on their production
machinery, and the reason was.
That the algorithm didn't scale very well.
It was a blend of many, many different
machine learning algorithms and it took a
long time to commute, compute particularly
on
the huge data sets that Netflix was
collecting.
And so they actually went with something
that was
a little less accurate, but quiet a bit
more scalable.
So that tells a lesson of accuracy isn't
always the best.
And only decision maker when trying to
build prediction algorithms.
Although that's often the one that gets
focused on the most.