After defining the question of interest,
the next
most important thing is to identify the
data set.
That will allow you to create the
best possible predictions, which are
machine learning algorithms.
So an example of a really successful
predictor
here in the United States is something
called FiveThirtyEight.
This was a blog that was designed to build
an election forecasting model
to predict who would win the Presidential
and other elections in The United States.
And to do that, the statistician behind
538, one of the most famous statisticians
in the world, Nate Silver, used polling
information from a wide variety of polls
and averaged them together to try to get a
best prediction of who is
going to win which votes and which states
in order to get the best vote.
A prediction of who would vote for who
when it came time for the election.
It was very successful in predicting both
the 2008 and 2012 elections.
This is an example of using like data to
predict like.
In other words, he took polling data from
organizations like
the Gallup polling agencies in the United
States, and he
took all that data that was asking people
directly, who
are you likely to vote for in the upcoming
election?
In other words, he used data where people
were asked the same question they were
going to
be asked when they went into the polls the
ballot and decide who they were going to
vote for.
And so, the one thing that he did, which
is
sort of clever and I think that it proves
his predictions
compared to a lot of other people, is that
he took
that data, and he recognized the actual
quirks of the data.
So, he realized that some polls were
actually biased in one way or the other.
In other words, a particular pollster
might ask questions that
led people to say that they would vote for
one candidate
more than the other, even when they might
not necessarily
vote that way when it came time to vote
for real.
So what he would do is, he would actually
weight the polls by
how close they were to being, sort of,
unbiased polls or accurate polls.
And so, this is an example where finding
the right dataset and combining it with
simple understanding
of what's really going on scientifically
can have
maximum possible benefit in terms of
making strong predictions.
And the key idea here is, if you want to
predict something about
X, use data that's as closely related to X
as you possibly can.
There are a bunch of other examples of
this.
So, one example is what's called
Moneyball, so this is
actually turned into a movie that starred
Brad Pitt, but
at the beginning, it was just, there were
some people
that were trying to predict how well
players would perform.
And in particular perform, how well they
would perform at
gaining wins for a baseball team in the
United States.
And what they would do is they would
actually
use information about that player's
performance, as well as other
players that were similar to them in the
past in
order to predict, predict how well that
player would perform.
So again, like predicting like.
This theme repeats itself in the Netflix
prize,
where people were trying to predict movie
preferences or
what movies people would like, and they
did that
based on the past movie preferences of
those people.
In other words, they found movie
preference data
and used it to predict movie preference
data.
It was also the background to the Heritage
Health prize, where the goal is to
try to predict which people would be
hospitalized, and they used data about
previous hospitalizations.
Again using data about the exact same
process
that they were trying to predict in the
future.
So, the closer that you can be to the
actual data about the process that
you care about, the more often than not
that you, the better your predictions will
be.
It's not necessarily a hard rule, so,
for example, people used Google searches
to try
and predict flu outbreaks, but this has
recently pointed out to have major flaws,
in
the sense that, if people's searches
changed,
or if the properties of the ways those
searches were connected to the flu
changed,
their predictions would actually be quite
far off.
And some people have suggested that Google
flu trends is not
necessarily a very good way to estimate
the prevalence of flu.
The looser the prediction, the harder the
prediction may be.
So, for example, Oncotype DX is a
prediction algorithm based on gene
expression, which is a measure of a
molecule inside of your body.
And, or actually a subset of molecules in
your
body, and it, they use that to predict how
long you will live or how well you'll do
under different therapies in when you have
breast cancer.
And so, here, the connections are little
bit looser, but it's
still a connection that you can definitely
make in your head.
The data properties do matter, so, for
example, if
you measure the people that would have
sort of
a high prevalence of flu-like symptoms,
you could do
that using CDC data or flu near you, and
algorithms like Google flu-trends might
overestimate the number of
flu case if there was something that was
causing
them to search for similar search terms
that had
nothing to do with how often they were
flu-related symptoms.
So this is an example where knowing how
the data actually
connects to the thing you're actually
trying to predict is crucially important.
This is, in fact, the most common mistake
in machine learning.
So, machine learning is often thought of
as
this black box procedure that computer
scientists have created
where they just pushed input data in one
end
and out comes a prediction in the other
end.
This is an example of a prediction that's
a little bit silly.
So, this was a, comes from a paper that
appeared in the New England Journal of
Medicine, and they plotted chocolate
consumption in kilograms
per year per capita on the X axis.
And on the Y-axis, the number of Nobel
prizes
per 10 million dollar, 10 million people
in the population.
And so you can see if there's a trend here
that, as you
consume more chocolate, you tend to get
more Nobel prizes per million people.
And so they reported here an R squared and
a P value suggesting this was a highly
significant relationship,
but you can think of a whole bunch of
other
variables that might relate these two
things to each other.
So, for example, you might eat more
chocolate if you
come from Europe, and these are mostly
European nations up here.
And the Nobel prize is given out by
European organization so
you might imagine that more European
people also win Nobel prizes.
This has nothing to do with the ability of
chocolate consumption per
se to predict whether you will get a Nobel
prize or not.
And so this is an example where, if you
just naively build a prediction algorithm,
you'll claim that you're being able to
predict
very well, but if the characteristics
change, so,
for example, if the Nobel committee starts
giving
out more prizes to, say, Asian nations as
opposed to European nations, you'll see
that this
prediction algorithm won't work very well
any more.
So the key point to take home is that, as
often as possible use like data to predict
like, and
when you're using data that isn't related,
be very careful
about interpreting why your prediction
algorithm works or doesn't work.