This lecture is about in sample and out of
sample errors.
This is one of the most fundamental
concepts that we deal with in machine
learning and prediction, and so it's worth
understanding the concept with a very
simple example.
So in sample errors, the error you get on
the same data you used to train your
predictor.
This is sometimes called resubstitution
error in the machine learning literature.
And in sample error is always going to be
a little bit optimistic,
from what the error is that you would get
from a new sample.
And the reason why is, in your
specific sample, sometimes your prediction
algorithm will tune
itself a little bit to the noise that you
collected in that particular data set.
And so when you get a new data set,
there'll be
different noise, and so the accuracy will
go down a little bit.
So what we do is we look at this out of
sample
error rate, this is sometimes called the
generalization error in machine learning.
And so the idea is that once we build a
model on a sample of data that we have
collected.
We might want to test it on a new sample,
on a
sample collected by a different person or
in a different time, in
order to be able to see what the sort of
realistic expectation
of how well that machine running algorithm
will perform on new data.
So almost always, out of sample errors is
what you care about.
So if you see a reported error rate for
date.
The error rate reported only on the data
where the machine-learning algorithm was
built, you know
that's very optimistic, and it probably
won't reflect
how the model will perform in real
practice.
In sample error is always less than out of
sample error, so that's something to keep
in mind.
And the reason is overfitting.
Basically, again, you're matching your
algorithm to the data that you
have at hand, and you're matching it a
little bit too well.
So sometimes you want to be able to give
up a little bit of accuracy
in the sample you have, to be able to get
accuracy on new data sets.
In other words, when the noise is a
little bit different, your algorithm will
be robust.
So just to show you a really simple
example, I thought I'd show you
in sample versus out of sample error's
with a kind of a trivial example.
So here's what I've done, I've taken this
again I've gone
to the kernlab package and I looked at the
spam data set.
Remember that was the data set where
we collected information about spam
messages, or
messages from robot and things like that,
and HAM messages, messages we actually
care about.
And what I do is I actually take a very
small sample of that Spam data set.
I just take ten messages and what I do is
I
basically look at whether you see a lot of
capital letters.
So I'm basically looking at the average
number of
capital letters that you observes in a
particular email.
And so I've plotted the first ten examples
here versus their index.
And so in red are all the spam messages,
in black are all the ham messages.
And so you can see, for example, that some
of the spam messages like this
one up here, have a lot more capital
letters than the ones that are ham
messages.
That sort of makes sense intuitively.
So we might want to build a predictor,
based on the average number of
capital letters, as to whether you are a
spam message or you're a ham message.
So one thing that we could do is build a
predictor that says if you have a
lot of capitals than you're a spam
message, and
if you don't then you're a non spam
message.
And here's what this rule could look like,
you could say if you're above 2.7, per
capital average we're going to call you
spam,
if you're below 2.40 you're classified as
non-spam.
And then one more, one thing we can do is
we can actually try
to train this algorithm very, very well to
predict perfectly on this data set.
So if we go back to these, this plot of
the
different values, you can see there's one
spam message right down here
in the lower right hand corner, that is a
little bit
lower than the highest non-spam value in
terms of this capital average.
So we could build a prediction algorithm
that would capture that spam value as
well.
And so what we would do then is, we would
make a
rule here that just picks out that one
value in the training set.
It says if you're between 2.4 and 2.45,
you're called spam as well.
And that's designed to basically make the
training set accuracy perfect.
And you can see if we apply this rule
to the training set, we actually do get
perfect accuracy.
So if you're nonspam, we perfectly
classify you as nonspam,
and if you are spam, we perfectly classify
you as spam.
An alternative rule would not train quite
so tightly to
the training set, but would still use the
basic principle of
if you have a high number of capital
letters then your
spam message, and so this rule might look
something like this.
If you're above 2.40, your cap, your spam
message, if
you're less than or equal to 2.40, then
you're nonspam message.
So this rule on the training set would
then miss that one value.
In other words, you could have a
prediction of nonspam for that one
spam message that was just a little bit
lower in our training set.
So overall, this looks like in that
training set that the accuracy is
a little bit lower for this rule, and it's
a little bit more simplistic.
So then we can apply it to all the spam
data.
In other words apply it to all the values,
not just the values that we
had in the small training set, and these
are the results that you would get.
So this is a table of our predictions on
the
the rows here, and in the columns that's
the actual values.
And so you can see the number of errors
that we make are the
errors here that are on the off-diagonal
elements of this little matrix that we
created.
So those are the number of errors that we
made, made.
And so what we can look at is that we can
actually look
at the average number of times that were
right using our more complicated rules.
So this is just the sum of the times that
our
prediction is equal to the actual value in
the spam data set.
And so that happens 3,366 times in this
data set.
And then we could also look at the
more simplified rule, the rule where we
just used
a threshold, and also look at the number
of
times that that's equal to the real spam
type.
And you can see about 30 more times, we
actually
get the right answer when we use this more
simplified rule.
So, what's the reason that the simplified
rule
actually does better than the more
complicated rule?
And the reason why is over fitting.
So, in every data set we have two parts,
we have
the signal component, that's the part
we're trying to use to predict.
And then we have noise, so that's just
random variation in
the dataset that we get, because the data
are measured noisily.
And so the goal of a predictor is to find
a signal and ignore the noise.
And in any small dataset, you can always
build a
perfect in-sample predictor just like we
did with that spam dataset.
You can always carve up the prediction
space in this, in this
small data set, to capture every single
quirk of that data set.
But when you do that, you capture both the
signal and the noise.
So for example, in that training set there
was one stem value
that has slightly lower capital average
than some of the non-span values.
But that was just because we randomly
picked a data
set where that was true, where that value
was low.
So that predictor won't necessarily
perform as well on new samples,
because we've tuned it too tightly to the
observed training set.
So, this lecture has two purposed.
One is to introduce you to the idea of in
sample and out of sample errors.
In-sample errors are errors on the
trainings that
we actually built with, and out of sample
errors are the errors on the data set
that wasn't used to build the training
predictor.
And also we introduced to you this idea of
over fitting.
In that we want to build models that are
simple and robust enough that
they don't actually capture the noise,
while they do capture all of the signal.