This lecture's about ROC curves, or
Receiver Operating characteristic curves.
These are very commonly used techniques to
measure
the quality or goodness of a prediction
algorithm.
So in binary classification, you're
usually predicting one of two categories.
So, again, you might be predicting whether
someone's alive or dead, or sick or
healthy.
You might also be predicting whether they
will click
on an ad or they won't click on that ad.
But your predictions often come out to be
quantitative.
In other words almost all the modeling
algorithms that we have won't
just assign you to one class or the other,
they might give you
say a probability of being alive, or a
prediction on a scale of
1 to 10 about whether you will click on
the ad or not.
The cut iff you choose gives different
results.
In other words, if we predict a
probability
that you're going to be alive is 0.7 and
we
say all the people above 0.5 will be
assigned to be alive, then that's one
prediction algorithm.
Alternatively if you say only people with
a probability
of about 28 will be predicted to be alive.
Then that will give you a different
prediction for that same person.
And the different cut offs will have
different properties, they will be better
at finding people that are alive or better
at finding people that are dead.
So if people use what's called an ROC
curve.
And so the idea is on the y axis what
they usually plot is one minus the
specificity in other words
the probability of being a false positive
and on the y
axis they plot the sensitivity over the
probability at true positive.
And so what they're trying to do then is
make a curve
where every single point along this curve
corresponds to exactly one cut off.
So for a particular cutoff, you get a
certain
probability of being a false positive or a
specificity, and that's this point, one
minus the specificity
is this point right here on this x axis.
At the same time, you get a certain
sensitivity, and that's this point here,
on the Y-axis.
And so, you can use these ROC curves to
define, whether an algorithm is good or
bad by plotting
a different point for every single, cutoff
that you
might choose, and then plotting a curve
through those points.
So this is an example of a couple of,
algorithms that are used to predict.
So these are examples of what real ROC
curves look like.
So, for example, if you want to look at,
say, the NetChop algorithm.
And you look at say 1 minus the
specificity is equal
to 0.2 in other words this specificity is
quite high, it's 0.8.
You can trace that number up and you can
get about here on the curve
the red curve in this case and that
corresponds to a sensitivity to only about
0.4.
So it's very highly specific but not very
sensitive.
And similarly if you move out here to the
right on the Y X axis.
You'll get less and less specificity, and
more and more sensitivity.
And so this curve tells you a little bit
about the tradeoffs.
Now although the curve tells you a little
bit about the tradeoffs,
you may actually want to know which of
these prediction algorithms is better.
And one way that people use to quantify
one curve versus
the other, is they basically calculate the
area under the curve.
In other words, they follow, say, the red
curve
here, and they trace the entire area
underneath that curve,
so that'd be this area down here, and so
that area quantifies how good, that
particular prediction algorithm is.
So, the higher the area the better the
predictor is, and some
standard, there are some standard values
that make sense to pay attention to.
So, if the area under the curve or AUC is
equal to 0.5 that's equivalent to a
prediction algorithm that's just
on the 45 degree line and that's
equivalent to basically randomly
guessing whether you're going to be a true
positive or false positive.
So, 0.5 is actually quite bad, anything
less
than 0.5 is actually worse than random
guessing.
So, it's worse than flipping a coin.
AUC of 1 is a perfect classifier, in other
words you get perfect sensitivity and
specificity for, for a certain value of
the
prediction algorithm, and so that's the
perfect classifier.
In general, it depends on the field, and
it depends on the
problem you are looking at, people often
think of an AUC above 0.8.
Could be considered to be something that's
sort
of a good AUC of a particular prediction
algorithm.
In general something to pay attention to
is what, how did you just look at
a ROC curve and decide whether it's a good
ROC curve or a bad ROC curve.
So remember the 45 degree line corresponds
to just guessing.
In other words, the sensitivity and the
specificity
match each other on this predictive o
line.
So, a perfect classifier goes at one minus
the specificity.
So, one minus the specificity of zero
means perfect specificity and
it jumps straight away up to perfect
sensitivity and then straight over.
So that curve represent a perfect
classifier
when it goes straight up to this corner.
So the further you are towards the upper
left
hand corner of the plot the better the ROC
is.
And the farther you are down to this
bottom right
hand corner of the plot the worse the ROC
is.
And so points along the, the, graphs along
the
forty five degree line or below are
considered pretty bad.
And you want your curve to look, to go as
straight up towards this
top left hand corner and over as over as
much as you possibly can.
So that's how you interpret an ROC curve,
which will be used later when
we're picking out particular values of,
predictors
of binary outputs that output quantitative
numbers.