Welcome to the course Practical Machine
Learning.
This is one of the funnest classes in the
Data Science specialization.
I'm very excited about all the ways you
can use date to predict, and I think it's
one of the areas that's probably the most
sort
of well known when you think about Data
Science.
This first lecture is going to cover the
motivation and pre-requisites for the
course and
give you a little bit of idea about where
we're going to be going.
So this course will cover the basic
ideas of machine learning and prediction,
and our
goal is to be very practical and very
hands on with our understanding of machine
learning.
And so the idea here is that we're going
to cover the
main techniques that lots of people use
and that you've maybe heard about.
Linear regression and random forests and
things
like that, but we're also going to cover
sort of the nitty-gritty details and the
practicalities of doing machine learning
and real examples.
And, so, we've got to start off with ideas
of, like, study design, so training versus
test sets, and deciding how do you
actually
build up a predictor in a real data set.
Then we'll talk about conceptual issues
like out of sample error
and over fitting, so you might have heard
of the fact
that some models are maybe a little tuned
to the noise
and that so it won't predict well on a new
sample.
And so we'll talk about how do you sort of
prevent those sorts of problems.
We'll also talk about things like ROC
curves or methods for
evaluating predictors for deciding whether
a predictor's any good or not.
And we're going to be focusing a lot on
the practical implementation of
these machine learning algorithms and also
these more conceptual issues in R.
And we're going to be using the caret
package for a large majority of that.
The caret package is a nice unifying
framework for
a lot of machine learning packages that
exist in R.
Those packages were built by a lot of
different people, and they
have different parameters and different
choices
that have been made by their developers.
And the caret package is sort of a nice
unifying framework for that.
This course does depend quite heavily on
the tools
that you've learned in the data
scientist's toolbox and
in R Programming, so if you haven't taken
those
classes already, they're highly encouraged
before taking this class.
It'll also be useful if you've taken
exploratory data
analysis, reporting data and reproducible
research, and regression models.
Those classes aren't required, but, a lot
of the material that
we'll cover in this class will, be related
to that picture, so
if you've seen it before, it might be a
little bit,
easier on you if you go through the
material in this class.
So who predicts things?
This is an important question.
I think an important motivator for this
class.
Basically, most organizations now use
machine learning in some simple
form or minimum and often in much more
complicated forms.
So here are a couple of examples.
Local governments might try to predict
pension
payments in the future so that they
know whether their revenue generation
mechanisms have
sufficient, funds, generated to cover
those pension payments.
Google might want to predict whether
you're going
to click on an ad so that they can
show you only the ads that, are most
likely to get clicks, and so it'll
increase revenue.
Amazon and Netflix and other companies
like that will show you
one movie and they want you to buy the
next movie.
In order to do that they want to show you
what you may be interested in.
Movies that you have seen this one movie,
so you might be interested in
these other movies, so they can kind
of keep you watching and again increase
revenue.
Insurance companies employ large groups of
actuary and statisticians
to try to predict your risk of all sorts
of different things, including death so
they can know
what's the right price to set insurance
premiums at.
And then please select Johns Hopkins where
I work will
also want to predict who's going to
succeed in their programs.
So which students that have applied to our
program will be most likely to be
successful.
All of these different prediction, tasks
are preformed by a
variety of different organizations, and
they're preformed at different levels.
So some of them are very complicated.
Predicting which ad you might click on
might have a whole bunch of
predictors, and it might be based on quiet
a complicated machine learning algorithm.
In some cases, it might be a lot simpler
in terms of what you're trying to predict.
And so, either way, it's an important
component of basically every major
organization these days.
So why would you predict things?
Well, one is glory.
Here's a picture of Chris Volinsky.
He's a member of the team that won the
Netflix Prize.
The Netflix Prize was a million dollar
prize that
was given out to a teen that could reduce
the
error that Netflix was making when they
were trying to
predict which new movie somebody might be
interested in seeing.
So Chris was a member of a large
organization of multiple teams that
blended their models together, and they
predicted the best and won the prize.
It's actually kind of a, a fascinating
story about how that happened.
And so, of course, they all got a lot of
sort
of nerd credit and a lot of glory for
winning these competitions.
And so that's one way, reason you might
be excited about being good at machine
learning.
You might also be excited because you can,
there's money in it.
So not only through organizations where
you can
earn a lot of money if you know how
to best predict which ads people will
click
on and so forth but even in these
competitions.
So, for example, this is the heritage
health prize.
And so this was a $3 million prize to the
team that
could best predict who would be admitted
to the hospital in a year.
And when you were trying to do this
prediction,
you would use information about the
previous hospitalizations from
previous years, and nobody actually won
three million dollars
but people did win quite a bit of money
from this prize over in the sort of the
interim prizes, and so people actually
both make money
through the competitions, but they also
spun off analytics
companies and organizations based on their
performance in these competitions.
In general, it's, it's now kind of a
sport.
Data science is a sport, particularly in
terms of prediction.
And so these are, this organization Kaggle
is
one of, many organizations that can host
these competitions
where you can try to predict, the outcome
of a particular experiment, or you try to
predict
all sorts of different things, and these
competitions
often run for a certain fixed period of
time
and often have a lot, of, of a little bit
of money on the line as well.
So, it can be a lot of fun, and there's a
ranking and
a leaderboard, so you can kind of get into
the fun of the competition.
This is a little closer to my area of
research, so you might also predict for,
the purposes of doing sort of better
medical
decision making and so Oncotype DX is a
prognostic gene expression signature that
can be measured
in women who have breast cancer, and it
can be used to predict how long they'll
survive, given a set of conditions that
they have.
So that can be useful for medical doctors
when making decisions about patients with
breast cancer.
This is a book that I find very useful.
Its a little bit advanced for this class,
although
a lot of the tools are incredibly useful
still.
It's called the Elements of Statistical
Learning, and
so this is a book that's actually, you
can get a free copy of the PDF from the
author's website, so that's very nice.
But if you do really like the book, I
encourage you to buy it as well.
The author's put a lot of effort on, into
it, and it's a great book, and so it
could be very useful in terms of having a
lot of information that we'll cover in
this class.
And then the package that I think we're
going to be
using by far the most in this class is the
caret package.
So the caret package combines a very large
number of predictors that
have been built in R, and it allows you to
sort of set
up training and test sets in a kind of a
unified framework that
prevents a lot of the problems that come
up when building prediction models.
If you want some more advanced materials,
so one place
to go would be the Machine Learning class
from Coursera.
And what I mean by advanced material is
sometimes you might be interested
in a lot more of the sort of mathematical
detail behind how these
algorithms work, or you might be
interested in a lot more of the
sort of high level machine learning
algorithms
that are on the very cutting edge.
And I think this class would be a great
place
for you to start learning about those with
some material.
This class, like I said, will cover the
basics and will focus
on getting you to the point from sort of
zero to 60.
And, in other words, it'll get you to the
point where you can use machine learning
tools in
your day to day, but it won't necessarily
cover
all the top level details of machine
learning algorithms.
There is actually a huge amount of
information available out there on machine
learning.
It's a very hot topic right now so so I
listed
her a bunch of links that sends you to
information at Quora.
It's from Science, from MIT, CMU, and
Kaggle, which will give you
a lot of information about how to do
machine learning in a variety
of different ways, and so, if this class
whets your appetite and
gets you excited about some of these other
things, that'd be great, too.