This lecture is about cross validation.
Which is one of the most widely used
tools, for detecting relevant features,
and for building models.
And estimating their parameters when doing
machine learning.
So remember the study design that people
frequently
use when building machine learning
algorithms, and evaluating them.
They take a data set.
In this case, it's the Netflix [INAUDIBLE]
study design.
So this is the.
1,000,000, 100,000,000 user item pairs,
where its
movies that were rated by specific users.
And they break that up into a training
data set, and then a test data set.
And remember that all of the model
building and evaluation by that.
People building the model will happen on
the training data, and then once, at
the very end of the competition, they
would apply it to the test data set.
So one problem that comes up that very
quickly, is that accuracy
on the training set is what's
called resubstitution accuracy is often
optimistic.
In other words, we're always picking,
we're trying a bunch of different
models, and we're picking the best one on
the training set, and
that will always be tuned a little bit to
the quirks of
that data set, and may not be the accurate
representation of what that.
Prediction accuracy would be a, a new
sample.
So, a better estimate comes from an
independent data set.
So in this case say the test set accuracy.
But there's a problem that, if we keep
using
the test set to evaluate the out of sample
accuracy.
Then, in a sense, the test set has become
part of the training set, and
we don't, still don't have an outside
measure, independent evaluation of the
test set error.
So to estimate the test set accuracy, what
we would like to use is, use
something about the training set, to get a
good estimate of what the test set
accuracy will be, so then we can build our
models entirely using the training set,
and only evaluate them once on the test
set, just like the study design calls for.
So the way that people do that is cross
validation.
So, the idea is, you take your training
set, just the training samples.
And we split that train, we sub split that
training set into a training, and a test
set.
Then we build a model on the training
set that's a subset of our original
training set.
And evaluate on the test set, that's
a subset, again, of our original training
set.
We repeat this over and over and average
the estimated errors.
And that's something like.
Estimating what's going to happen in, when
we get a new test set.
So again, the idea is we take the training
set, and we split
the training set itself up, into training
and test sets over and over again.
Keep rebuilding our models, and picking
the one that works best on the test set.
This is useful for picking variables to
include in the model.
So, again, we can.
Now, fit a bunch of different models, with
various different variables included,
and use the one that fits best on these
cross validated test sets.
And then we can also pick the type of
prediction function
to use, so we can try a bunch of different
algorithms.
Again, pick the one that does best on the
cross validation sets.
Or we can pick the parameters in the
prediction function and estimate them.
Again, we can do all of this because,
eventually,
even though we're, we're tr, sub splitting
the training
set into a training set and a test set,
we actually leave the original test set
completely alone.
Where it's never used in this process.
And so when we apply our ultimate
prediction algorithm
to the test set, it'll still be an
unbiased measurement.
Of what the auto sample accuracy will be.
So, the different ways that people can use
training and test sets.
One example is they do random subsampling.
So, imagine that, every observation we're
trying to
predict is arrayed out along the, this
axis here.
And the color represents whether we
include it in the
training set or testing set, so again,
this is only
the training samples, and what we might do
is just
take a subsample of them, and call them
the testing sample.
So in this case, it's the light gray bars
here, are
all the samples in this particular
iteration that we call test samples.
Then we would build our predictor on all
the dark gray samples.
And so, again, this is only within the
training set.
We take the dark gray samples and build a
model, and then
apply it to predict the light gray
samples, and evaluate their accuracy.
We can do this, for several different
random subsamples.
So this is a ra, one random sampling.
And then this second row is the second
random sampling.
And this third row is the third random
sampling.
Do that over and over again, and then
average what the errors will be.
Another approach that's commonly used is
what's called K-fold cross validation.
So the idea here is we break our data set
up into k equal size data sets.
So, for example, for three fold cross
validation, this is what it would look
like.
So here's.
The first data set, right here, then
there's a middle
data set right here, and the last third
data set right
here, and so what we would do is on the
first
fold, we would build a prediction model on
this training data.
And we would apply it to this test data.
Then we would build a training our model
on the, just the dark gray
components of this second fold, and apply
it to the middle fold for evaluation.
Then finally, we would do the same thing
down here.
We would build our model on this dark gray
part, and apply it to the light gray part.
And again, we would average the errors
that we
got across all of those experiments, and
we would get
an estimate of [COUGH] the average error
rate that
we would get in an out of sample
estimation procedure.
So again, all of these model building and
evaluation are happening
in, within the training set, which we've
been subs divided into a.
Sub training set and a sub testing set to
evaluate models.
Another very common approach is called the
leave
one off, out cross validation, and so
here, we
just leave out exactly one sample, and we
build the predictive function on all the
remaining samples.
And then we predict the value on the one
sample that we left out.
Then we leave out the next sample, and
build on all the remaining values.
And then predict the sample that we left
out, and so forth
until we've done that for every single
sample in our data set.
So again, this is another way to estimate
the out of sample accuracy rate.
So some consideration is, first of all,
for time series data, this doesn't
work if you just randomly subsample the
population, you actually have to use
chunks.
You have to get blocks of time that are
all contiguous, and that's because, one
time point might
depend on all the time points that came
previously,
and you're ignoring a huge, rich structure
in the data.
If you just randomly take samples.
For k-fold cross validation, the larger
the k that
you take, you'll get less bias, but more
variance.
And the smaller k that you take, you'll
get more bias, but less variance.
In other words, if you took a very large
k, say for example a ten-fold cross
validation or a 20-fold cross validation,
that means
you'll get a very accurate estimate of
the.
Of the bias between your predicted values,
and your true values.
But it'll be highly variable.
In other words, it'll depend a lot on
which random subsets that you take.
For smaller ks, we won't necessarily get
as good
an estimate of the out of sample error
rate.
And that's because, you're only leaving
one sample out.
And so you're using most of your data to
train your model.
But there'll be less variance.
In other words, if you do in the extreme
case.
If you have for exampleonly two cross,
two-fold
cross validation, there are only a very
small.
Number of subsets that can make up a
two-fold cross validation.
And so you get less variance.
Here, the randomless sampling must be done
without replacement.
In other words, we're subsampling our data
sets.
That's, of course a disadvantage, because,
it means that we
have to break our training setup even
further to smaller samples.
If you do random sampling with
replacement, this is called the Bootstrap.
That's something that you've learned about
in your early.
Inference classes, if you've taken those.
The bootstrap, in this particular example,
will in general, underestimate the error
rate.
And the reason why is because if you do
the bootstraps, you sample
with replacement from some of your
samples,
some samples will appear more than once.
And so, in more, samples appear more than
once, that means
that if you get one right, you'll
definitely get the other right.
And so, you actually get underestimates of
the
error rate, and this can be corrected but
its rather complicated, the way to do
that,
is with something called the 0.632
Bootstap, which
is not exactly a great name for a method,
but it explains, it sort of explains
how you can account for the fact that you
have this underestimate in the error rate.
You can do any of these approaches when
you go models
with the care package like we'll be
learning in this class.
If you cross validate to pick predictors,
you again must estimate the errors on
an independent data set, in order to get a
true out of sample value.
So in other words, if you do cross
validation to predict
your model, or to pick your model, the
cross validated error rates.
Since you always picked the best model,
will not necessarily be a
good representation of what the real out
of sample error rate is.
And the best way to do that, is again, by
applying
your prediction function, just one time,
to an independent test set.
[SOUND]