This lecture's about the caret package,
which is
a very useful front end package that wraps
around
a lot of the prediction algorithms and
tools
that you'll be using in the R programming
language.
So the caret package can be found here at
this website that I linked to here at
the bottom, or you can just Google caret R
package, and you'll be able to find the
package.
The functionality that's built into the
care package are some of the following.
So, for example, we can use the
preprocessing tools in the caret package
to clean
data and get the features set up, so that
they can be used for prediction.
We can also do, sort of cross validation
and data splitting
within the training set, using the
create DataPartition and create TimeSlices
functions.
We can also create training and test sets
with the training and predict functions.
And we can use those to train data sets at
train prediction functions and apply them
to new data sets.
We can also do model comparison using the
confusion matrix function, which will
give you information about how well the
model's did on new data sets.
There a large machine learning algorithms
that are built into R, so
these range from very popular statistical
machine learning algorithms like linear
discriminant
analysis and regression to much more
widely used algorithms in computer
science,
like support vector machines,
classification and
regression trees, or random forests or
boosting.
All of these algorithms are built by
a variety of different developers, all
coming from
different backgrounds, so the interfaces
that each of
these sort of prediction algorithms is
slightly different.
As one example of this, consider
this class of different prediction
algorithms that
you could have applied, so everything
from linear discriminate analysis down to
boosting.
And so for each of these different
algorithms,
you can imagine creating an object called
objnr.
That object will have a different class,
say
a linear discriminate analysis or glm and
so forth.
And for each of these objects, we can try
to predict, and if we apply the predict
function, we
have to put it pass slightly different
parameters each
time in order to get the prediction of the
outcome.
So, for example, from the GLM package, we
have to say type
equals response to get the prediction of
the response from that model fit.
Or, for example, if we want to use rpart,
we want
to predict with type equals probability in
order to predict the response.
In each case, they're a little bit
different, and the caret
package provides a unifying framework that
allows you to predict using just
one function and without having to specify
all the options that
you might care about in order to get the
same prediction out.
So here's a quick example, using the caret
package.
We'll go into the details of how this is
done very specifically in later examples.
So here we've loaded in the caret package,
and we've loaded
the kern lab package as well to get the
spam data set.
And so, what we can do first is partition
the data setup into a training and a test
set.
Here I'm going to use the spam type, and
I'm going to
split it into the, training set and the
test set.
I'm going to say we're going to use about
75% of
our data to train the model and 25% to
test.
Then what I can do is I can actually
subset the data
into the training data using the in train,
bit, the in train, object
that comes out from create data partition,
and I can create the testing
data set by finding all those samples that
aren't in the training set.
Then this will give me a subset of that
data that are
just for training and a subset of the data
that adjust for testing.
And you can do this with sort of a simple
interface.
Next you can fit a model, so here I'm
going to use the
train command from the caret package, and
so again I'm trying to predict type.
And I use the tilde and the dot to say use
all
the other variables in this data frame in
order to predict the type.
And I tell which data set I want to build
the training model on,
and so, in this case, the training data
set we created on the previous slide.
And then I just tell which of the methods
that I'd like to use, and
so you can use GLM or you can use a bunch
of other different models.
And so what this does is it'll create a
model fit
from the train function, and as we use the
3451 samples
in a training set and the 57 predictors to
predict which
class you're belonging to based on a
model, a GLM model.
And so what it can do is it can do a bunch
of different ways
of testing whether this model will work
well
and using it to select the best model.
And in this case it used resampling.
And it does bootstrapping with 25
replicates, and it corrects
for the potential bias that might come
from bootstrap sampling.
So once we fit that model, we can actually
look at the model, and so
the way we can do that is look
at the finalModel component of the
modelFit object.
And the way you do that is you take the
modelFit object,
and then you type dollar sign and then
always the same finalModel.
It will tell you what are the actual
fitted values that you got for that GLM
model.
Then you predict on new samples by using
the predict command.
Again, it's a unified framework, so we
just type predict.
We pass it the modelFit that we got from
the train, function in
carrot, and we pass it which data we would
like it to predict on.
So in this case, the new data is the
testing data.
When you do that, it will give you
a set of predictions that correspond to
the responses,
and you can use those to try to evaluate
whether your model fit works very well or
not.
One way that you can do that is by
calculating the confusion matrix,
so that's using this confusion matrix
function, and so note the capital M here.
Don't miss that when you're typing
confusion matrix.
Then you pass in the predictions that you
got from your model fit.
And then the actual outcome on the testing
samples.
So in this case, it was the type or
whether it was spam or ham message.
And then it will record the confusion
matrix.
So it'll tell you a table for which of the
cases that you predicted to be nonspam or
actually nonspam, which is the cases where
it was
spam, and you predicted to be spam and so
forth.
And then it gives you a bunch of summary
statistics.
So for example, the accuracy, a 95 percent
confidence interval for the accuracy,
and then a bunch of information about how
well they correspond in other categories.
So, for example, the sensitivity and the
specificity of that.
So the confusion matrix function wraps a
bunch of different accuracy measures
that you might want to get out when you're
evalutating the model fit.
For a lot more information about caret,
we're going to cover a lot of it
in this class in terms of how do you
actually apply the caret package.
But I found that these tutorials are
actually very nice, and they can
be very useful for covering material that
we don't cover in this class.
And there's also a very nice paper in the
journal of
statistical software that introduces the
caret
package if you want further information.