This lecture's about one of the most
direct and
simple ways to perform machine learning
using regression modeling.
If you've taken the regression modeling
class in the data science
specialization, then a lot of this
material will be familiar to you.
We're just using it in the service of
performing prediction.
So the key idea here is that we're just
going to fit a simple regression model.
If you don't know what that is, don't
worry about
it, I'll explain it briefly in the rest of
the lecture.
But the idea is that basically we're
going to fit a line to a set of data.
So that line will consist of basically
multiplying a
set of coefficients by each of the
different predictors.
And so then we get new predictors or
new covariance and we multiply them by the
coefficients
that we estimated with our prediction
model and then
we get a new prediction for a new value.
This is useful when that linear model is
nearly correct, in other words.
When the relationship between the
variables can
be modeled in a linear way, in
other words as a function of lines, then
this is a useful way to predict.
It's very easy to implement, and it's also
quite easy
to interpret compared to many machine
learning algorithms in the
sense that, it's, you're fitting a set of
lines to
a data set and the lines are relatively
easy to interpret.
It can have poor performance in nonlinear
settings.
So it's usually used in combination with
other machine learning algorithms on
complicated examples.
So we're going to be using data on
eruptions of geysers.
And so, they're, geysers are have a
waiting time in between their different
eruptions and there's an amount of time
that they actually erupt for, so
there's a data set that we can load in
very easily that contains
some information on eruptions for a
particular
geyser, Old Faithful in the United States.
Famous geyser.
So we can load the caret package and load
the data for this eruptions.
And I'm going to set the seed so that all
the
analysis that I'm going to perform after
this can be reproduced.
Then I create a training set and a test
set just like usual.
I create a training set because we're
going to be building models.
Only in the training set and then applying
them in the test set.
And so, if you look at the data set, if
you look in the training
set, you can see that we have just two
variables, so it's a very easy example.
We have an eruption time and a waiting
time.
So the waiting time is the time between
eruptions and the
eruptions is the length of time that the
geyser was erupting.
If I make a plot of these two variables, I
see waiting time here on the x axis.
And duration here on the y axis.
You can see that there's roughly a linear
relationship.
Or you can imagine drawing a line through
this that
predicts relatively well, the duration
time from the waiting time.
So we can do that by basically fitting a
formula that's just a,
a line so remember the formula for a line
is going to be the
eruption duration here is equal to a
constant or an inter, what people call
an intercept term, plus another constant
times
the waiting time plus the error term.
So.
As you saw in the previous slide, even if
a
line fit through the middle of the data
looks like
it's sort of a reasonable approximation to
the relationship, there's
obviously not, the points don't exactly
fall in a line.
And that's why we allow for some error in
our model.
The error models, everything that we
didn't have,
we didn't measure, we didn't understand
about the relationship.
And so we can use the lm command in r to
fill linear model.
So lm, relates the eruptions, that's
going to be
the outcome variable that you're trying to
predict,
the tilde says we're going to predict it
as
a function of everything on this side of
the.
The code right here, we're going to use
the waiting data.
We're going to build that model using the
data from
the training set, so if we do that, if we
do that, we get a summary of the output
and
the point, the part to look at, assumes
the prediction here.
Are these estimates so the estimate here
is just the intercept that's the constant.
So that's B0, in this formula, and the
waiting time estimate here is B1 in
this formula, and so if we get a new
prediction, we just add minus 1.79.
Plus 0.073 times whatever our new waiting
time is
and that produces our new prediction for
the expected duration.
So this is what the model fit looks like
and so I'm basically
again, I'm plotting the train set, the
waiting times versus the eruptions and
then I plot the fitted values and the way
I do that is,
I can extract that from the linear model
object nar with an LM1$fitted.
Fitted will give me the fitted values and
then I plot that
versus the, the predictor variable that I
used to predict the values.
So here this is the waiting time plotted
versus duration.
The points come from this first plot
command and then
the line that is fit right here, the black
line.
Speaker 1: Comes from this lines command
that's adding a line of faded values.
So you can see just like we saw previously
there's a line
that's a reasonably good representation of
the relationship between these two
variables.
Obviously it's not perfect, the points
don't lie exactly on the
line, but it's a reasonably good capture
of the main data set.
So, to predict a new variable, we just
again, like I said,
take the estimated value for b0 and the
estimated value for b1.
We usually denote those with little hats
above the values.
And then we just multiply them together
using the formula from the previous page.
Remember we don't have, in this formula,
we don't have an error term.
Because we don't know what the error term
is for this
particular value, so we just use the parts
that we can estimate.
So to get those values extract those
values from
the linear model object you can use the
coef.
Command that gives you the coefficients
which is the name that
we use for those two variables, the
estimates for those two variables,
and so coeflm11 will give you the
intercept, a value beta hat
zero, and put lm2 will give you beta hat 1
a value.
Fit for, the waiting time.
And then, suppose we have a new waiting
time that's 80.
Then the prediction that we get out is
4.119 as the time for the eruption
duration.
So, another thing that we can do is we can
actually predict using that LM object.
You don't actually have to, every time,
extract the coefficients and multiply them
together.
So if we create a new data set.
Which is a data frame that has one new
value that we want
to predict, so we say we have waiting time
equal to just 80,
then if I type predict and I pass it the
fitted model from
the training set, and the new data set,
new data frame we created.
It'll give me the prediction for the new
value.
And it matches, so it's using the same
formula in this predict command,
that you would use if you actually
calculated out the prediction by hand.
So another thing to look at, is.
So, remember, we built this model on the
training set, just like we always do.
And we want to see how it does on the test
set.
So here, I have, separated the data into,
Two separate
sets the training and test sets and I made
two plots.
On the left there's a plot of the training
data and on
the right there's a plot of the test data
and so the
training data I plot the waiting time
versus the duration and then
I put the model fit in and it's a
reasonably good model fit.
That's to be expected because it.
Is the exact data that we use to build the
model.
Then I also plot the test data set and so
over here, this is the line
that you get, the predictions that you get
from the model built on the training set.
So you can see that it doesn't quiet
perfectly fit
the data anymore like it did in the
training set.
It's a little tilted underneath over hear,
but that's to be expected
because, the test set is a slightly
different set of data, but
as you can see it still captures the
overall trend or the
overall part of the variation that can be
explained by the waiting time.
The next thing to do is to get the
training and test set errors.
So, to get the training set error, we get
the fitted values,
lm1$fitted, remember lm1 was the object we
actually fit to fit the model.
And the fitted values were the predictions
that we get on the training set.
Then we can subtract the actual values of
the eruption duration on the training set.
Square them, sum them up and take the
square
root and that gives us the root mean
squared error.
If you remember that from our lecture on
the types of errors we could have.
So it basically measures how close the
fitted values are.
To the, real values.
And we get a value of 5.752.
We can also calculate the root mean square
error on the test set.
And so, the way that we do that, is, we
calculate, we predict again
now, using this LM fo, LM object that we
can fit on the training set.
But now we pass it the new data set, the
test data set.
So now this is predicting values on the
test data set and we subtract
off our actual values since we know what
they are on the test data set.
Square them and sum them up.
And since we didn't use the test set at
all when we built are algorithm.
This is a more realistic estimate of the
root mean square error that you would get
on a new data set compared to the value
that we got on the training set.
And just like always, the test data set
error
is almost always larger than the training
set error, because.
Again we're moving to a new set of values
that
weren't used to calculate the model, so
that's represents the
added error, or error and variability you
get when you
move to a new data set out of sample
error.
The other thing that you can do that a
nice component of
using linear modeling for prediction is
that you can calculate prediction
intervals.
So, again, here I'm just calculating on,
on, calculating a new set of predictions.
For the test data set from using our
linear
model that we've built on the training
data set.
And I say that I also want a prediction
interval
out and so that's just an argument that
I've passed
to the predict function and then if I
order the
values for the test data set and plot the
test.
Waiting times versus eruption times.
I can also add lines that show not only my
predictions, that's
what I've got here in this black line that
shows the predictive values.
But I can also show an interval that is
the interval that captures.
Percent of where we the region where we
expect
the predicted values to land, so we expect
most
of the predicted values to land in between
these
two red lines if our linear model is
correct.
And so this.
Shows you a little bit about the range of
possible values we could predict.
Not just a single prediction, which can be
useful for giving you an
idea of how well your model is likely to
do on new, predictions.
It'll tell you what are the range
of possible predictions that you might get
out.
You can do the same thing in the caret
package.
Again the caret package, I've shown you
how to do it now by
hand but you can also very easily do it
with a caret package.
I use the train function in the caret
package to build the model.
And so again I, the eruptions is the
output, outcome,
waiting time is the predictor and they're
separated by this tilde.
And then I say which data set I want to
build
the model on and for the method, I tell
it, Linear Modeling.
So if you do a summary of that final model
fit so the final model is the part of
the modFit objects that was created by
Train that tells
you the exact final model that's being
used for prediction.
And again, it looks very similar to the
model that we fit
by hand, it's minus 1.79 for the intercept
and 0.07 for the waiting
time.
So regression modelling can be done with
multiple covariants
as well, and we'll have a lecture on that.
But you can also combine it with
all other prediction and machine learning
methodology.
Again, it's sort of a good quick and dirty
method for use.
It does miss.
Getting a higher mis-classification error
when the relationship isn't necessarily
linear.
A lot of prediction is covered with,
regression modeling is covered in these
books, and would be a good place to go if
you want more information.
[SOUND]