One of the most important components of
building a machine learning algorithm or
prediction model
is understanding how the data actually
look
and how the data interact with each other.
So, the best way to do that is actually
by plotting the data, in particular
plotting the predictors.
So for this example we're going to be
using this wages data.
So the wages data is actually data from
the ISLR package.
Which you can find at this link.
And it's from the book Introduction to
Statistical Learning.
So we're going to be looking at this data
and seeing how we can use it for
prediction.
So if I load the ISLR package.
Again I'm going to have to install it
first and then I can load it.
And I also load the ggplot2 package
because
we're going to be using that for some
plotting.
And the caret package, because we're going
to be using that for model building.
The wage data is actually in the ISLR
package, and
I can load it with data and a capital w
Wage.
And then I can look at a summary of that
wage
data to look at all the different
variables that are in there.
So we have the year of the data that's
collected.
The age of the person who is the data is
collected on.
In this case, it's only male people in
this data set,
the marital status of those people, their
race, education, the region where
they were, the data was collected is just
the Mid Atlantic
region, and then the different kinds of
job classes and their health.
So this gives you a little bit of
information about what
the type of data that we're going to be
looking at.
And you can already see that we've
detected a few interesting
characteristics of this data just by
looking at a summary here.
We know that they're all men.
We know that they're all in the Mid
Atlantic region, for example.
So then what we do is again, just like
always,
we're going to build a training set and a
test set.
Even before we do exploration, we're
going to set aside the
testing set and we're not going to use it
for anything
until we actually look at the data at the
end
of the, model building experience, and
apply it just one time.
So we're going to do all our plotting in
the training set.
So one example is to use this feature
plot, plot that comes from the caret
package.
So this plot will plot basically all of
the features against each other so this
plot
looks a little bit confusing for this data
so I thought I'd just go through it.
So here I'm, using as the outcome I'm
saying the outcome is the wage.
And then I'm going to look at all
these different variables, age, education,
and job class.
So, first of all I have this y variable so
that's
the outcome that we care about, and here
the different variables.
I've got age, education, you can't read it
very clearly in this
plot, but if you make it yourself you can,
and job class here.
And so, what this plot is, this is the
plot
here of the outcome y versus the job class
here.
So you can see, you can do that for every
box, so if you want to see the
plot of job class versus education, that's
this plot here.
And it's the same plot here, only with the
axis reversed and so forth.
So it shows you all of the variables that
you have here, plotted against each other.
And in particular, what you are looking
for, here are all the
plots corresponding to each of the
variables plotted versus the y variable.
And you're looking for any variable that
seems
to show a relationship with the y
variable.
So, for example, you can see that there
seems to
be a trend here between education and
salary, for example.
So this is one way that you can look at
all the data.
Another thing that you're going to use is
either Qplot, function
in the ggplot2 package or just the plot
function base R.
So here I'm plotting age versus wage, and
so you can see again it
appears that there seems to be some kind
of trend with age and wages.
But you also see, one thing that
you notice frequently from making plots
like this.
Here's some very strange patterns.
So you see there's this big chunk up here
of observations that
appear to be very different than the
relationship down here for these chunks.
So one thing that we might want to do is
try to figure out why
there, there's that strange relation
between ages
and wages before we build our, our model.
So, one thing that we could do is, for
example,
using the ggplot2 package, color that plot
by different variables.
So again, I plotted age versus wage, so on
the x axis is age, on the y axis is wage.
But now I've colored it by the job class.
And so you can do that with, by
passing the parameter color to the two
plot function.
And so what you see now is that most of
the individuals that are up
in this other chunk, come from the
information
based jobs as opposed to the industrial
jobs.
So that might explain a lot of the
difference here between, these two big
classes of observations.
So this gives you a way to sort of
detect variables that might be important
in your model.
Because they show, variation in the data.
So you can also add regression smoothers.
So, for example, now, what I've done is,
I've again made a
plot of age versus wage, but now I've
colored it by education.
And so then what I can do is I can use
the geom_smooth function to apply a linear
smoother to the data.
You would've learned about this in
Exploratory Data Analysis, but
if not, you can just see the function
right here.
And so what that does is for every
different education class, it
fits a linear model, so you can see
there's a purple line here.
And that corresponds to people with
advanced degrees and then you can see for
example a green line here, that
corresponds
to people with some college and so forth.
And so you can see if there's a different
relationship for different age groups.
The other thing that you might that is
often very useful is to break up things
like
the wage variable into different
categories cause sometimes it's
clear that specific categories seem to
have different relationships.
The way I tend to do that is with the cut2
function, that's in the Hmisc package.
So if you load the Hmisc package and then
use cut2, you can tell
it with the g parameter how many groups to
break the data set into.
And it'll break the data set up into
factors based on quantile groups.
So all of the observations that land
between 20.1 and
91.7 on the wage variable will get
assigned to this
factor level and then all the values
between 91.7 and
118.9 will get assigned to this group and
so forth.
And so, what you can do now is you can
actually
use that to, in order to make different
kinds of plots.
So now, suppose I wanted to plot wage
versus, oh sorry, wage groups versus
age, I can now, use qplot again but now I
can pass it the box plot geometry.
And then I can say okay, I want to see the
plot of these different wage groups
versus age and sometimes that can make it
easier to see different trends that are
emerging.
For example, you can see here a little
bit more clearly the relationship between
age and wage.
The other thing you might want to do is
you might want
to add on top of the box plots, actually
the points themselves.
The reason why you might want to do
this is because sometimes box plots can
obscure how
many points are being shown here and so
one thing that you can do is you can
say, pass it both box plot and jitter and
you can have it, arrange the plot so you
can see both the box plot itself and you
can see the box plot with points overlaid.
So that's what grid arrange is doing, it's
actually generating the two plots.
So p1 was the plot that we made on the
previous slide.
And p2 is the plot we made here with
points overlaid.
And grid arrange makes two plots side by
side.
So you can see here from the dots that
there's a large number of dots in each of
the different boxes and so that suggest
that this
trend, any trend a user may actually be
real.
If you observe just one of a few dots in
the boxes it means maybe
that that particular box isn't very well
representative of what the data actually
looked like.
Another thing that's very useful is you
can use the cut variable,
the factorized version of the continuous
variable to look at tables of data.
So here I'm making a table comparing this
factor
version of wages to the job class and so I
can see for example that there are more
industrial jobs
in the lower wage variable than there are
information jobs.
And that trend reverses itself for the
highway jobs.
There are fewer industrial people and more
information people.
You can also use prop table to actually
get the proportions in each group.
So here it's the proportion, by passing it
one,
I say I want to get the proportion in each
row.
So if I passed it at two here, it would
give me the proportion in each column.
So here I see that 62% of the low wage
jobs go, correspond to industrial, and
37%, 38% correspond to information.
And so you can use that to get an
idea of how those proportions change
across different wage levels.
Finally you can use density plots to plot
the values of continuous predictors.
So here again I'm using the qplot
function.
I'm plotting the wage variable, and I'm
plotting a density plot, versus education.
So this basically shows where the bulk of
the data is.
So on the x axis is the wage.
And on the y axis is sort of the
proportion of
the variable that falls into that bin of
the x axis.
And so you can see, for example, the high
school grads tend to have more values that
are down here in the lower part of
the range, and the advanced degree folks
tend to
be a little bit higher, and there's also a
group, outgroup over here that tends to be
very high for both the advanced degree as
well
as the college grads which is shown in
blue.
So sometimes density plots can show things
that box plots can't necessarily do.
It's also easier to overlay multiple
distributions when you're doing density
plots.
In other words, if you break things up
into a bunch of different groups, and you
want to see how all the distributions
change
by group, density plots can be very
useful.
So, one thing to keep in mind is to make
your plots only in the training data.
The test set, again, can't be used for
exploration.
That would be similar to training your
model on the test
set, which, as we should, talked about
previously, will lead to overfitting.
Things that you should be looking for in
these
plots is imbalance in the outcomes of the
predictors.
If you see all of the predictors tend to
be one
value in the one outcome group, and not
another outcome group.
Then you see that's a good predictor.
But if you see that, you only have three
of one outcome and 150 of the other
outcome, that means it's going to be very
hard
to build an accurate classifier between
those two classes.
You're looking for outliers or weird
groups outlying the data
that might suggest that there are some
variables you're missing.
And groups of points that are not
explained by any of the predictors.
Skewed variables which you're going to
want to transform and
make look better, more sort of nicely
normally distributed if you're
using things like regression models but
that may not matter
as much as if you're using more of machine
learning methods.
For more information on plotting in
general
you can look at the ggplot2 tutorial.
You could also take the exploratory data
analysis class in
this data science specialization or you
can look at the
caret visualization tutorial, because
that'll give you a little bit
more information about prediction specific
plots that might be useful.