This is a brief lecture about some about
the training control
options that you have when training models
using the Caret package.
For this lecture, we're going to be using
the
SPAM example again, just to illustrate how
these ideas work.
So we load the Caret package, the kernlab
package and the we attach the spam data
set.
Then we use the createDataPartition
function to
create a set of indices corresponding to
the
training set, and we set about 75% of the
data to be in the training set.
Then we define training and testing sets
using those indicator functions.
So usually what you would do when you fit
a model is basically just use the train
function, like
this, where you basically set all of the
defaults to
be whatever defaults that the train
function chooses for you.
Other than maybe the method that you're
going to be
using to fit and which dataset you're
going to be using.
You can go a little bit further than this,
though, for
example you can use a large set of options
for training.
So here are a couple of them.
One, you can use this preProcess parameter
to set a bunch of pre processing options.
We'll talk about that in a future lecture.
You can also set weights, in other
words you can upweight or downweight
certain observations.
This is particularly useful if you have
very unbalanced training set
where you have a lot more examples of one
type than another.
You can set the metric so by default for
factor variables.
In other words, for categorical variables,
the default
metric is accuracy that it's trying to
maximize.
For continuous variables it's the root
mean squared
error like we talked about in a previous
lecture.
So you can also set a large number
of other control parameters using this
trControl parameter here.
And you have to pass it call to this
particular
function trainControl, which we'll talk
about in a couple of slides.
So the metric options are built into the
train function
for continuous outcomes or RMSE or root
mean squared error.
You can also use RSquared, this is the r
squared that you
get from a regression model, if you
remember that from the inference class.
RSquared is a measure of linear
agreement between the variables that
you're predicting.
And the variables that you predict with.
Linear agreement is very useful if you're
using linear regression, and things like
that.
It may not be so useful if you're doing
more non-linear things, like random force,
and so forth.
Accuracy is the fraction correct.
So that's just the number that you get
correct.
And that one of the, that's the
default measure of accuracy for
categorical outcomes.
You could also tell it use Kappa, which is
a measure of concordance.
I've linked here to a definition of that
measure.
It's not, it's a much, a more in depth,
more complicated
measure that's frequently used in some
competitions like Kaggle and other
competitions.
The trainControl argument allows you to be
much
more precise about the way that you train
models.
You can tell it which method to use for
resampling the data,
whether it's bootstrapping or cross
validation,
which we'll talk about in a minute.
You can tell it the number of times to do
bootstrapping or cross validation.
You can also tell it how many times to
repeat that whole process if you want to
be careful about.
Repeated cross validation, you can tell at
the size
of the training set with this p parameter,
and
then you can tell it a bunch of other
parameters that depend on the specific
problems you're working on.
So, for example, for time course data,
initialWindow
tells you the size of the training data
set, the size of the number of time points
that will be in the training data.
And a horizon is the number of time points
that you'll be predicting.
You could also have it return the actual
predictions themselves
from each of the iterations when its
building the model, you
could also have it return a different
summary, use a different
summary function and a default summary if
you like it to.
And then you can set preprocessing options
as well as
things like prediction bounds and can set
the seeds for all
the different resampling layers, this is
particularly used for, if
you are going to be parallelizing your
computations across multiple cores.
We are not going to cover that too
extensively here but if you're.
Training models on large numbers of
samples
with a high number of predictors using
parallel processing can be highly useful
for
proving the computational efficiency of
your analysis.
For resampling, there are a bunch of
methods that are offered
so this is again passed the trainControl
function, you can use standard
boot strapping, you can use boot strapping
that adjusts for the fact
that multiple samples are repeatedly
resampled
when you're doing that sub sampling.
This will reduce some of the bias due to
the bootstrapping.
You can use cross validation which is a
method that we talked about in previous
lectures.
You could also use repeated cross
validation if you
want to do sub cross validation with
different random draws.
You can use leave one out cross validation
and
remember there's a bias variance trade off
between using.
Large number of folds and, and smaller
number of folds when doing cross
validation.
You can also tell it the number of
bootstraps samples or the number of
subsamples to take
and the number of times to repeat that
subsampling if you're doing something like
repeated cross validation.
All of these parameters can be set.
In general the defaults work pretty well,
but if you have
large numbers of samples, or you have a
model that requires
fine-tuning across a large number of
parameters, you may want to increase,
for example, the number of
cross-validation
or bootstrap samples that you take.
Finally, an important component of
training these models is setting the seed.
So what I mean by that is, most of
these procedures rely on random resampling
of the data.
And if you rerun the protocol over again,
or
rerun the code over again, you will get a
slightly different answer because there
was a random draw
that was created when you were doing cross
validation.
If you set a seed, a random number seed,
what that will do
is that will ensure that the same random
numbers get generated each time.
Its a little bit difficult concept to get
your head around
but the idea is that the computer is
generating pseudo random numbers.
And if you set the seed it will
generate the same sequence of pseudo
random numbers again.
So you can, its very useful, often to set
the overall seed.
This is the seed for the entire procedure
so you can get repeatable results.
If you're doing parallel computation, you
can also set the seed for each resample.
You can do that with the seed argument to
the trainControl function.
Seeding each resample is particularly
useful for parallel fits but is often not
necessary when you're doing all your
processing
that, in a way that isn't parallel.
So here's an example of that.
If I set the seed using the set.seed
function in r,
and then I give it a number, an integer
number, it
will set a, a seed that's consistent for
performing this analysis,
and so it'll generate a set of random
numbers that is consistent.
So then if I fit my model like this, then
when it generates bootstrap samples,.
It will generate those bootstrap samples
according to the
random numbers that come from this seed,
if I
then reset the seed again, and fit the
model
again, now with the different number
modelFit3 instead of modelFit2.
Then I will get exactly the same bootstrap
samples
and exactly the same measures of accuracy
back out again.
This is important when you're training
models and
then you want to share your training data
set
with someone else and ensure that you get
the same answer when they run the same
code.
There are more information about this in
the Caret tutorial, which I think is very
good, and also in this document about
model training and tuning with the Caret
package.