So this lecture is about data slicing, and
you might use data slicing
either for building your training and
testing sets right at the beginning of
your prediction function creation, or you
might use it for performing cross
validation
or boot strapping within your training
set, in order to evaluate your models.
So again, we're going to be using the
caret
package, so I've loaded the caret package
here, and
I'll also lured, loaded the kernlab data
set
again, just so I can load the spam data.
So again, this is a data set where we're
trying
to predict whether emails are spam or ham
and we
have a bunch of variables that measure how
many times
a particular word appears, or how often
capital letters appear.
So one thing that we can do right off the
bat is
use createDataPartition, to separate the
data set into training and test sets.
If I do this, what'll happen is I tell it
which outcome I want to
split on, so in this case I want a split
based on the type.
And I say, I want to create a data set
that's 75%, is
allocated to the training set, and 25% is
allocated to the testing set.
So what happens then is that the
inTrain variable gets assigned an
indicator function
that I can use to sub, subset out the
training set and the test set.
So, the training set we create by
subsampling this spam data set, the
spam data frame, into only those samples
that appear in the training set.
And then, the testing set is all the
remaining
samples, which you can do in r by using
this
minus sign to indicate that they're, all
the samples that
don't appear in this index set in the
inTrain variable.
So now, that's one way to split your data
into a training and test set right at the
beginning.
You might also want to do something like
cross validation where you
split your training set into a bunch of
smaller data sets.
The K-folds that you'll then use to do
cross validation.
So, one way that you can do that is
with this createFolds function in the kay
caret package.
So, what you do is again, you pass it the
outcome that you want to split on.
So again, this is the spam type variable.
And then we tell it the number of folds
that we'd like to create.
In this case, I say I would like to create
10 folds.
And in this case, I also tell list=TRUE,
which means it will return each
set of imbecies corresponding to a
particular fold as a set of as a list.
And, you can tell it to either return
the training set or not return the
training set.
So, for example, if I do this, then I've
got a bunch of different folds that I've
created.
And for each one, I want to cre, check the
length of that fold.
And so, for example, in Fold01 there are
4141 samples.
And in Fold02, there's 4140.
And so forth.
So it split the data set up into ten
folds, where
each fold has approximately the same
number of samples in it.
Then what I can do is if I want to look at
which
samples appear in the first fold, I take
the first element of the
fold's list, and so, when I look at that
list, it's the first
10 elements correspond to the, actually
the first 10 elements in the sample.
In other words, this is split up in order
into the first to 4100 samples in the
first fold.
The second 4140 samples in the second fold
and so forth, so you can actually look
at which of the indices corresponding to
the
training set and the test set within those
K-folds.
You can have it also return the test set,
or you can have it return the training
set.
So remember I'm, here I'm splitting the
data set about 75, 25 into
training and test sets and so what I can
do is I can say returnTrain=FALSE.
And then what it'll do is it'll actually
return just the test set samples.
So here, you can see that there's much
smaller number of samples in each
fold, and that's because most of the
samples are going to the training set.
And again, you can look at, for fold 1,
what are
the samples that actually correspond to
the testing set in that fold?
You can also do resampling, so if instead
of doing a full cross validation, you
want to do something like resampling or
bootstrapping,
you can use the createResample function,
resample function.
Again, you tell it how many times you
would like to resample the data
and whether you would like a list out, or
vector out, or matrix out.
And so, what this will tell you is, again,
which samples correspond to a particular
fold, and since we're doing resampling
now, you
might get some of the same values back.
So, for example, in the first fold, you
actually get the sample three repeated
three different times in that fold because
you're re-sampling with replacement from
the values.
You can also use it to create time slices.
So if you're analyzing data that you might
be using for forecasting, you can use
it to check what are the time slices where
you take continuous values in time.
So here, I've created a time vector that's
1 to 1000.
The integer is 1 to 1,000 and I want to
create
slices that have a window of about 20
samples in them.
And I want to say I'm going to predict the
next 10
samples out after I take the initial
window of 20.
And so, in the first training set, I can
see that there are 20 values.
And so, there are actually 20 samples that
have been created
in the first window that we're going to be
using to predict.
And if I looked at this test set, it gets
cut off here, but
there would be 10 samples and there would
be next 10 samples, 21 to 30.
And the next subsample would be shifting
that over and
getting a next time slice, but it gets
continuous sets of
numbers all in a row so that you can use
the time varying component of the sample
in order to predict.
There's a lot of information in the caret
tutorials about
how to do time slicing, and we'll show
various examples
of it when we build prediction functions
in the rest
of this class, and your homework will
cover this as well.
The paper introducing the caret package,
again, also has
a lot of information about how to do time
slicing, and how to do data slicing for
both
creating training and test sets, and for
cross validation.