This lecture is about covariate creation.
Covariates are sometimes called predictors
and sometimes called features.
They're the variables that you will
actually
include in your model that you're going
to be using to combine them to predict
whatever outcome that you care about.
There are two levels of covariate
creation, or feature creation.
The first level is, taking the raw data
that you
have and turning it into a predictor that
you can use.
So the raw data often takes the form of an
image, or a text file, or a website.
That kind of information is very hard to
build a predictive model around when you
haven't summarized the information in some
useful
way into either a quantitative or
qualitative variable.
So what we want to do is take that raw
data and turn it into features or
covariates which are variables
that describe the data as much as possible
while giving
some compression and making it easier to
fit standard machine-learning algorithms.
So the idea here is, so suppose you have a
email,
this is an email, an example email here on
the left.
And so it's very hard to plug the email
itself into
a prediction function, because most
prediction functions are based on the idea
of taking a small number of variables and
building a quantitative model
around them and it doesn't work for a free
text for example.
So the first thing that you need to do is
create some
features, and those features are just
variables that describe the raw data.
So in this case, in the case of an email,
we
might think of different ways that we
could describe this email.
For example, when I calculate the average
number of
capitals that are in the email, in this
case 100%
of the letters in the email are capital
letters,
you might say what's the frequency a
particular word appears.
So for example, you might say, how often
does you appear?
And you appears twice in this email, so we
say that we calculate two for this email.
That's a feature.
You might also calculate the number of
dollar signs.
This might be a really good predictor of
whether an email is spam or not.
And so here you can see there are a large
number of dollar signs,
there are eight of them, so we calculated
another feature of that data set.
So this step, the raw data of the
covariate, usually involves a
lot of thinking about the structure of the
data that you have
and what is the right way to extract,
extract the most useful
information in the fewest number of
variables that captures everything that
you want.
The next stage is transforming tidy
covariates.
In other words, we calculated this number,
say capital
average, the average number of capitals in
the data set.
But it might not be the average number
that's
related very well to the outcome that we
care about,
it might be the average number of capitals
squared or
cubed, or it might be some other function
of that.
And so the next stage is transforming
the variables into sort of more useful
variables.
So for example, if we load the kernlab
data
and the spam data set, we can take the
capital average, so the, this is basically
this variable
right here, the fraction of letters that
are capitals.
And we could square that number, and
assign it to a new
variable, capital average squared, that
might
be useful later in our prediction
algorithm.
So those are the two steps in creating
covariates.
So the first step the raw data,
the covariate really depends heavily on
the application.
So like I showed you on the previous
slide, in an email case, it
might be extracting the fraction of times
a word appears or something like that.
In a case of voice, it might be knowing
something about
the frequency or the timbre of which
voices are typically fall.
In the case of images, it might be
identifying features of the images.
So if it's faces, where are the noses or
the ears or the eyes are?
And it will depend greatly what your
application is.
And the balancing act here is definitely
summarization versus information loss.
In other words, it, the, the best features
are features that capture only the
relevant information in,
say, the image or the email, and throw out
all the information that's not really
useful at all.
And so the idea is that you have think
very carefully about how to
pick the right features that explain most
of what's happening in your raw data.
So some examples here, for text files, it
might
be the frequency of words or frequency of
phrases.
There's this cool site, Google ngrams,
which tells you about the
frequency of different phrases that appear
in books going back in time.
For images, it might be edges and corners,
blobs and ridges for example.
These are all ideas about how do you
identify different structures in an image.
For websites it might be the number and
type of images, where buttons are, colors
and videos.
This is a huge area of importance in web
development which is called
A/B testing, which is called randomized
trials
and statistics, which is basically showing
different
versions of a website with different
values of these different features and
predicting
which one will introduce a more clicks or
get more people to buy products.
For people you can imagine features of
people are their height, weight, hair
color, etc.
It's basically any summary of the raw data
that you can make as a potential feature.
And often this involves quite a bit of
scientific thinking and business
acumen to know what the right covariates
are for a particular problem.
So the more knowledge you have of a
system,
the better job you'll do at feature
extraction in general.
In general it's a good idea to have a
really clear understanding of why
this set of data is useful for, to
predicting the outcome you care about.
So there's this balance between
summarization and information loss, and in
general, it's better to err on the side of
creating more features.
You lose less information and then filter
some
of those features out during your
model-building process.
This can all be automated and has
been automated in various different ways,
but you
generally have to use a lot of
caution when using that approach because
sometimes a
particular feature will be very useful in
the training set that you created but
won't
be very useful in a new set of data and
the test set won't generalize well.
So the second level is taking tidy
covariates, so these are features you've
already created on the data set, and then
creating new covariates out of them.
Usually this is transformations or
functions of the covariates,
that might be useful when building a
prediction model.
This can sometimes be more necessary
for methods like, regression, or support
vector
machines that might depend a little bit
more on what the distribution of
the data are, and a little bit less for
things like classification trees,
where the idea here is you
don't necessarily have as much model-based
prediction.
In other words, you don't depend quite so
much on the data looking a particular way.
On the other hand, in general, it's a good
idea to spend
some time making sure you have the right
covariates in your model.
So you, when you create these functions or
decide on these
functions, you have to do it only in the
training set.
This is a common theme of machine
learning.
Building features can only happen in the
training
set, it can't happen in the test set.
Later when you apply your prediction to
your function to the test set, you
will make that same function of the
covariate so you can apply your predictor.
But the original creation or thinking
about what covariates to build has
to happen only in the training set,
otherwise you'll lead to overfitting.
And the best approach I've found is
through exploratory analysis,
so basically making plots and making
tables of the data, and
trying to understand what are the patterns
of variation in
your data set, and how they might relate
to the outcome.
When you're using the care package or
doing this analysis in r, the new
covariates
need to be added to data frames so that
they can be used in downstream prediction.
And it's important to make sure that the
names of the new variables are
recognizable so that you can use the same
name on your testing data set.
So here's an example data set.
So here we're loading in this data from
the ISLR package, and
we're loading the care package and we're
getting this data on wages.
So here again I'm going to build a
training and test set
so I can do all the covariate creation in
the training set.
So I use the create data partition
function to
create the index, indices for the two data
sets.
Then I separate the data into a training
set and into a test set.
So one idea is that's very common when
building machine learning algorithms is to
turn covariates that are qualitative, or
factor
variables, into what are called dummy
variables.
So you probably learned a little bit about
this in your
regression modeling class if you've taken
it through this data science
specialization.
But the basic idea is suppose we have a
variable, in this
case let's look in the training set at the
variable called job class.
So that job class has two different
levels, it's either industrial, or it's
information.
So one thing that we could try to do is
try to plug that variable directly into
a prediction model, but the values of that
variable will be a actually a set of
characters.
It'll either be industrial, or it'll be
information.
And it's sometimes hard for prediction
algorithms to use those
qualitative information variables, in
order to actually do the prediction.
So one thing we might want to do is turn
it into a quantitative variable, and the
way that you can do that with the
care package is with this dummy variables
function.
So basically it says we're going to pass
in a model so the outcome is wage.
Job class is going to be the predictor
variable, and tr, training
set is the set where we're going to be
building those dummy variables.
And then if you predict, if you use the
predict function, this dummy's object and
a new data set,
in this case we're just going to apply it
to
the training data set, you get, two new
variables out.
So the first is an indicator that you are
industrial, and the second is an indicator
that you're information.
If the indicator that you're industrial is
one, it
means that for that person, they had an
industrial job.
If it's zero it means for that person,
they had not an industrial job.
So the same thing is true for information.
If it's zero that means they had not an
information
job, and if it's one, they have an
information job.
So, in this case, where's there only two
different levels
of this variable, there's only industrial
and information, then whenever
you're one for industrial, you're zero for
information, and whenever
you're zero for industrial, you're one for
information and so forth.
But if you had three variables here, it
would
probably have, every column would have two
zeros, because
those are the two classes you don't belong
to,
and a one for the class that you belong
to.
So this is taking these factor or
qualitative variables and turning em into
quantitative variables.
Another thing that happens is that some of
the variables are basically have no
variability in them.
So it's often that you'll create a feature
for example, if you create a
feature that says for emails, does it have
any letters in it at all?
Almost every single email will have lots,
have at least one
letter in it, so that variable will always
be equal to true.
It's always got letters in it, so it has
no
variability and it's probably not going to
be a useful covariate.
So one thing that you can use is this near
zero variable or function in carrot
to identity those variables that have very
little
variability and will likely not be good
predictors.
So you apply it to a dataframe that's the
training data set.
And here I'm telling it to save the
metrics so
that we can see how it's calculating what
the variables are.
So, for example, here we can see that it
tells us the percentage of unique
values for a particular variable, so in,
in this case the variable has
about 0.33% unique values, and it's not,
not near zero variable, near zero variance
variable, but for example, sex, the
variable
sex, only is basically males and so
it has a very low frequency ratio.
In other words, it's basically all one
category, and so, this ends up being
a near zero variable and so, it will be,
you could use this column of the matrix
to throw out all those variables like sex
and, in this case, like region that are
variables that don't really have any
variability in
them and shouldn't be used in prediction
algorithms.
So this is a nice way to throw
those sort of less meaningful predictors
out right away.
The other thing that you might do is, so
instead of
fitting, if you do linear regression or
generalized linear regression as
your prediction algorithm, which we'll
talk about, in a future lecture,
the idea will be to fit, basically
straight lines through the data.
Sometimes, you want to be able to fit
curvy lines, and one way
to do that is with a basis functions, and
so you can find
those, for example, in the splines
package, and so one thing that you
can do is create this, the bs function
will create a polynomial variable.
So in this case, we pass at a single
variable, in this case, the training set,
we take the age variable, and we say
we want a third degree polynomial for this
variable.
So when you do that, you essentially get,
you'll get a three-column matrix out.
So this is now three new variables.
This variable corresponds to age, the
actual age values.
There are scales for computational
purposes.
The second column will correspond to
something like age squared.
So, in other words, you're allowing it to
fit a quadratic relationship between age
and the outcome.
And the third column will correspond to
age cubed, so
you allow a cubic relationship between age
and the outcome.
So this'll, if you include these
covariates
in the model instead of just the
age variable when you're fitting a linear
regression, you allow for curvy model
fitting.
So just to show you an example of that,
here I
fit a linear model, you'll remember that
from your linear modeling class.
So, the wage is the outcome.
Again the tilde tells you what's we're
predicting it with.
Here we pass it that BS basis, in other
words, we
pass it all the predictors that we
generated from the polynomial model.
So in this case, it's age, age squared and
age cubed.
And then we can plot the age data versus
the wage data.
So that's age on the x axis, wage on the y
axis.
And you can see that there's, kind
of, a curvilinear relationship between
these two variables.
And so we can plot age and the predicted
values
from our linear model, including the, the
curvy terms, polynomial
terms and you see you get a curve fit
through
the data set as opposed to just a straight
line.
So that's one way that you can generate
new variables is
by allowing more flexibility in the way
that you model specific variables.
So then on the test set, you'll have to
predict those same variables.
So this is the idea that's incredibly
critical
for machine learning when you create new
covariates.
You have to create the covariates on the
task data set
using the exact same procedure that you
used on the training set.
So you can do that by saying I'm going to
predict from this
variable that I created using the BS
function, a new set of values.
This is the testing set age values.
So these are the values that I'm going to
actually plug in to
my prediction model when I'm testing it
out on the test set.
This is as opposed to creating a new set
of, predictors based on
just applying the BS function directly to
this age variable, which would be creating
a new set of variables on the test set
that isn't related to
the variables that you created on the
training set and may introduce some bias.
So a little bit about this idea, these
ideas
and some future reading for you, So level
one
feature creation is basically all about
science or, application
specific knowledge, I've found that the
best way to do
it, find things for a specific
application, that I
haven't talked about here, or that you
don't know
about, or you're new to, is Googling
feature extraction
for the type of data that you're trying to
analyze.
Feature extraction for images.
Feature extraction for voice.
Things like that.
you, you can also just look up that
particular data
type and see as much information as you
can about it.
In particular you're looking for what are
the salient
characteristics that are likely to be
different between individual samples.
In general you want to err on the side of
overcreation of features
because you can always filter them out
later in the machine learning algorithm
process.
In some applications like images and
voices,
it's often both possible and pretty much
necessary
to create features that aren't necessarily
just
things that you imagine out of your mind.
It's very hard to know exactly what the
right components of
an image to include as features in a
model, and so there
are things like you may have heard of deep
learning which is
basically a way of creating features for
things like images and voice.
And this is a nice tutorial I've linked to
here, that
kind of explains how that feature creation
process works for those things.
But in general, automatic feature creation
requires an equal level of thinking to
make sure that the features being
generated
by your feature creation process make
sense.
Level 2 feature creation covariates to new
covariates can be
done a lot with the preProcess components
of the caret package.
You can create new, new covariates using
basically any of
the functions in r, if they make sense to
you.
The key is, again, making lots of plots
and doing exploratory analysis
to see where the connections between the
predictors and the outcome are.
You can create new covariates if you think
they will improve fit.
Again, you can kind of err on the side of
overcreation of features,
but sometimes features just are, are, sort
of, nonsensical and you shouldn't create
them.
Be careful about overfitting in the sense
that
if you create lots of features that are
particularly good for just your training
set, they
may not work well in the test set.
And so a good idea is if you overcreate
lots of features
to do some filtering before you actually
apply your machine learning algorithm.
This tutorial on preprocessing with caret
is very good.
It's a good place to start for really
basic preprocessing.
And if you want a flit spline model like
the
ones I talked about with flexible curves,
you can use
the gam method in the caret package which
allows smoothing
of multiple variables using a different
smooth for every variables.
And more on feature creation and data
tidying is in the
getting data, Getting and Cleaning Data
course from the Data Science
specialization.