This is a lecture a lecture about
preprossings, preprocessing covariants
with principal components analysis.
The idea is that often you have multiple
quantitative
variables and sometimes they'll be highly
correlated with each other.
In other words, they'll be very similar to
being the almost the exact same variable.
In this case, it's not necessarily useful
to include every variable in the model.
You might want to include some summary
that
captures most of the information in those
quantitative variables.
So, as an example I'm going to use the
spam data set again.
So I've loaded the caret package here, and
I've loaded
the kernel app package, and loaded the
spam data set.
I again, create a training and test set
and I'm going to
perform only the operations on the
training set that I'm doing here.
So that all exploration and model creation
and
feature building has to happen in the
training set.
The first thing that I do is that I
leave out just the 58th column of this
training set.
Which in this case is the outcome.
So I'm looking at all the other predictor
variables.
And I calculate the correlation between
all those columns.
The correlation between all predictor
variables.
And I take its absolute value.
So I'm looking for all the predictor
variables that that have
a very high correlation or are very
similar to each other.
Every variable has a correlation of 1 with
itself.
So I'm not interested in those variable.
You know, removing variables that have
high
correlations with themselves, since they
all do.
So I set the diagonal of those matrix,
that comes out to be equal to 0.
That's basically just setting the
correlation
between variables with itself, equal to 0.
And then I look, which of these variables
have a high correlation with each other?
In other words, which of the variables
have a correlation greater than 0.8?
So it turns out two variables have a very
high correlation with each other.
They are the num415 and num857.
So it's how, if the number 415 and
857 appears in the email and frequently
appears together.
This is likely because there's a phone
number that has similar variables there.
So, if I look at the spam dataset, at the
columns 34
and 32, which I got from getting that from
the previous correlation variable.
I see that it's these two variables, these
two columns that are highly correlated
with each other.
And if I plot those two columns against
each other, I see exactly what I'd expect.
So, the frequency of four 415 and 857 is
incredibly highly
correlated, this basically lie perfectly
on a line with each other.
So, as the number of 415 appears more
frequently, so does the number 857.
So the idea is, including both of these
predictors
in the model might not necessarily be very
useful.
And so, the basic idea is, how can we take
those variables
and turn them into, say, a single variable
that might be better?
And one idea is to think about it as a
weighted
combination of those predictors that
explains most of what's going on.
So the idea is to pick the
combination that captures the most
information possible.
And the benefits here are, you're reducing
the number
of predictors you need to include in your
model.
So that's nice.
And you're also reducing noise.
In other words, you're averaging or
combining
variables together, so you might reduce
them together.
So you do this in a clever way, you
actually gain quite a bit by doing
principal component analysis.
So one idea to think about is just.
Basically what you're trying to do is
figure out a
combination of these variables that
explain close to the variability.
So just as an example, here's a
combination I could do.
I could say I could take 0.71 times the
415 variable plus 0.71 times 857 variable.
And create a new variable called x.
Which is basically the sum of those two
variables.
Then I could take the difference of those
two variables.
By basically doing 0.71 times 415 minus
0.71 times 857.
So this is basically adding, x is adding
the
two variables together, y is subtracting
the two variables.
So then if I plot those variables versus
each other, when I add
them up, that's the x-axis, and when I
take the difference, that's the y-axis.
And so you can see most of the variability
is happening in the x-axis.
In other words there's lots of points all
spread out across the x-axis,
but most of the points are clustered right
here at 0 on the y-axis.
So that almost all of these points have a
y value of 0.
So, the adding the two variables together
captures most of the
information in those two variables and
subtracting the variables takes less
information.
So the idea here is we might want to
use the sum of the two variables as a
predictor.
That will reduce the number predicted that
we will
have to use and renew some of the noise.
So there are two related problems to how
you do this in a more general sense.
And so the ideas are find a new set of
variables based on the variables
that you have that are uncorrelated and
explain as much variability as possible.
In other words from the previous plot,
we're looking for
the x variable which has lots of variation
in it.
And not the y variable which is almost
always 0.
So if you put the variables together in
one matrix, create the best matrix with
fewer variables.
In other words this is lower rank if
you're talking mathematically that
explains the original data.
These two problems are very closely
related to each other.
And they're both the idea that, can we use
fewer variables to explain almost
everything that's going on.
The first goal is a statistical goal and
the second goal is a data compression
goal.
But they're also, they're both very useful
for machine learning.
So there's two related solutions and
they're very similar to each other.
So if x is a matrix with a variable in
each column, and an
observation in each row, like a data in
frame you usually have in R.
Then the singular value decomposition is a
matrix decomposition.
So it takes that data frame X, and breaks
it up into
three matrices, a U matrix, and D matrix,
and a B matrix.
And the V, the columns of U are called the
left singular vectors.
And the columns of B are called the right
singular vectors.
And D is a diagonal matrix.
Those are called the singular values.
You will learn about this in getting data
or exploratory data analysis if you've
taken those classes.
The principle components are equal to the
right singular
vectors if you scale the data in the same
way.
In other words, the solution to both of
those problems that I talked
about on the previous slide is the same if
you do the right scaling.
So the idea here is, these variables in V
are
constructed to explain the maximum amount
of variation in the data.
So, just to show you how this works in
a real example, suppose we take that spam
data set.
And we just take those two variables that
were highly correlated with each other.
Variables 34 and 32.
So then we do principal components.
Same as the singular value decomposition
on the, on that
small data set that just consists of those
two variables.
If we plot the first principle component
versus the second principle component.
We see a plot that is very similar to the
one that I showed you earlier.
Where the first principal component looks
like adding the two variables together.
And the second principal component looks a
lot
like subtracting the two variables from
each other.
So why would we do principal components,
instead of just adding and subtracting?
Well, principal components allows you to
perform this operation,
even if you have more than just two
variables.
You may be able to reduce all of the
variables down into a very small number
of combinations of sums and differences
and weighted
sums and differences of the variables that
you've observed.
So, using principal components can let you
look at a
large number of quantitative variables and
reduce it quite a bit.
The one thing that you can also look at
it in this principal component object is
the rotation matrix.
Which is basically how it's summing up the
two variable to get each of the principal
components.
And so here you can see why I put 0.71
in the sum and the difference on the first
slide.
So, principal component one is just 0.7081
times num14, 415, and 0.7061 times num857.
Principal component two is just the
difference
again, by multiply by 0.7061, and minus
0.7081.
So basically, in this particular case the
first principal component, the one
that explains the most variability is just
adding the two variables up.
And the variable that explains the second
most variability in these
two variables is the taking the difference
between the two variables.
So in this spam data we can do, actually
do
this for a more variables than just the
two variables.
This is why principal components may be
useful.
So here, I'm creating a variable that's
just going to
be the color we're going to color our
points by.
So it's color equal to black if you are
not
a spam and color equal to red if you're a
spam.
And this variable here, or this statement
here
calculates the principal components on the
entire data set.
So you'll notice that I've applied a
function
of the data set, the log 10 transform.
And I've added one.
I've done this to make the data look a
little bit more Gaussian.
Because some of the variables are normal
looking, because some of the variables are
skewed.
And you often have to do that
for principal component analysis to look
sensible.
So then I calculated the principal
components of the entire data set.
So in this case I can now again
plot principal component one, versus
principal component two.
Principle component one is no longer a
very easy addition of two variables.
It might be some quite complicated
combination
of all the variables in the data set.
But it's the combination that explains the
most variation in the data.
Principle component two is the combination
that explains the second most variation.
And principal component three explains the
third most and so forth.
So if I plot principal component one.
That's just a variable that I've
calculated.
Versus variable principal component two
that's another variable that I've
calculated.
Then I color them by the spam indicator.
So, whether each point, so each of
these points corresponds to a single
observation.
The red ones correspond to spam
observations
and the black ones just ham observations.
You could see that in principal component
one space, or along the principal
component one.
There's a little bit of separation of the
ham messages from the spam messages.
In other words the spam messages tend to
have
a little bit higher values than principal
component one.
So this is a way to reduce the size of
your data set while still
capturing a large amount of variation
which
is a, a, the idea behind feature creation.
You can do this in caret as well.
So you can do it using the pre-process
function.
So this is just using, basically doing
a similar type operation with a caret
package.
You pass the pre-process function.
The same data set you did before.
You tell it what methods you use.
In this case you tell it to use principal
component analysis or PCA.
You tell it the number of principal
components to compute.
And then, what we can do is you can
actually calculate the
values of each new principle compo, so the
principle component are two variables.
There is principle component one,
principle component two.
And they're basically a model that you fit
to the data.
So the idea is that if you get a new
observation you have
to predict what the principle component
will look like for that new variable.
So we pass this pre-processed object and
the data set,
to the predict function and that gives us
the principle component.
If we plot them versus each other, you see
spam pc
1, so that's principle component 1 versus
principle component 2 here.
And again you see a little bit of
separation.
Between the ham and the spam messages, in
both principle component one and principle
component two.
You can do this, like I showed you before,
by
doing preprocessing with the method PCA,
using the preProcess function.
And then you can create training
predictions by using the predict function.
And then, fitting a model that relates
the training variable to the principal
component.
So here I haven't used the full training
set as the data for fitting my model.
I've just [UNKNOWN] the principal
components for the model fitting.
In the test data set you have to use the
same principal
component that you calculated in the
trained video set for the test variables.
So the idea here is we again pass at
the pre-process object that we calculated
in the training set.
But now we pass at the new testing data.
So this predict function is going to take
the principle components we calculated
from training.
And get the new values for the test data
set on those same principle components.
So then, what you can do, is you can
predict.
The, using the modelFit on the original
data using the test principal components.
And you can use the confusionMatrix
argument in caret to get the accuracy.
And so, here we calculated a relatively
small number of
principal components, but still have a
relatively high accuracy in prediction.
So principal component analysis can reduce
the number of variables while maintaining
accuracy.
So the other thing that you can do is you
can
actually decide for this analysis to not
use the predict function separately.
You can build it right into your training
exercise.
So if you take the train function from the
caret package, and you pass it in a
training set.
But you tell it to pre process with
principal component analysis.
It will do that pre-processing as part of
the training process.
And then when you do the prediction on the
new data set you just pass
it a testing data set and will, it will
actually calculate the PC's for you.
The reason why I showed you the more
elaborate way
of calculating the PC's first and passing
them to the model.
Is so that you can see what's going on
under the hood.
When you pass a command like this, to the
train function in the caret package.
So this is most useful for linear type
models.
This includes linear discriminant
analysis, linear
and generalized linear regression, things
like that.
It can make it a little bit harder to
interpret the predictors.
In the case where I only had two
variables, it was just the sum
and the difference of those variables, it
was very easy to predict what that meant.
In general though, if you do principal
components on a large number of
quantitative variables.
In each principal component might be quite
a complex weighted sum of
the variables you've observed and so it
could be very hard to interpret.
You have to watch out for outliers.
Outliers can really wreak havoc on
calculating principal components.
So you do that by looking at
an exploratory analysis first and
identifying outliers.
Doing transforms, like I did the log ten
transform of
the data, you might do Box Cox
transformations as well.
And again, plotting predictors to identify
problems is the
key place to figure out where this is
working out.
For more information, you can see the
exploratory data analysis class
where we talk about principal component
analysis and SVD in more detail.
And this book the Elements of Statistical
Learning has
a quite nice, if a little bit technical
overview.
Of how principal components work for
machine learning.