This lecture's about two things.
First it's about predicting with
regression and using
multiple covariates, but more importantly
it's about exploring a
data set and trying to identify which
predictors are
the most important to include in our
prediction model.
So we're again going to be using the wages
data to try to
predict the wages of a group of men that
come from the mid Atlantic.
This data set is available at the ISLR
package which you can find here.
And it comes from the book Introduction to
statistical learning.
So the first thing that we do is that we
load
the data set in, and so here is the ISLR
data set.
We're also loading the ggplot2 package for
some
exploratory analysis, and we're loading
the caret package.
We're doing prediction, and we're going to
subset the data set for exploration
purposes to
just the part of the data set that isn't
the variable we're trying to predict.
So we select out the log wage variable,
which is
the variable that we're going to be
predicting in this analysis.
Then we can look at a summary of the data
set and
so we can already see some features, for
example, we saw before,
that this data set has only males included
in the data set
and that for example the region is
entirely peopled from the mid Atlantic.
So to do a little bit more exploration, we
first
need to train subset things into the
training and test sets.
So we use that with the Create Data
Partition function.
And we subset into a training and test
set.
And so we're going to do all of our
exploration again on the training set.
Because when we're building models, we're
not going to use any of the test set.
We're only going to apply it once.
So the first thing that you can do is a
feature plot.
So this feature plot says, shows a little
bit
about how the variables are related to
each other.
Sometimes this plot is useful and
sometimes it isn't.
In this particular plot it's a little bit
hard
to see because everything is so squished
together but if
you make it on your own, by using this
function
you'll see that it's a little bit easier
to see.
So, for example, you can see that there
appears
for the job class there appears to be this
group,
appears to be a little bit higher than
that
group for the job class in terms of the
outcome.
And you can see that there is, at least
for this age variable the relationship to
the outcome.
Again there seems to be some outlier
group, two separate groups here that gives
us some indication that we might be able
to use that variable to predict.
So the first thing that we can do is plot
the variables versus weight age.
So this is plotting the wage variable
versus the age
variable and you can see that there
appears to be
some kind of trend which we saw in the
previous
lectures, but there also is this set of
points that's
outlined up here, and so the idea is that
that
set of points that's outlined up there
might be, something
that we can predict, but we would have to
figure
out what variable it is that, is
representing that chunk.
So, one way that you can do that is, you
plot one variable, one predictor, age
versus the outcome, wage.
And then you color the points by another
variable, in this case job class.
And you can see for example that it
appears that most of these points up
here are blue instead of pink and so
that means they come from the information
group.
So, this gives us some indication that the
information variable might be able to
predict at least
some fraction of the variability that's in
that top class up at the top of the plot.
You can also color it by education.
So, here I'm just doing a q plot again.
So I'm plotting age versus wage.
And I'm telling it to color the plot by
education.
And, again, I'm only using the training
set because we're trying
to, only look at training set for our
development of our model.
And you can see that the advance degree,
also explains,
a lot of the variation up here in the top
group.
And so, some combination of, degree, and,
class of job, could explain why, the
relationship
between age and wage isn't just a perfect
relationship down here, in one big cloud.
So the next thing that we can do is fit a
linear model with multiple variables in it
and so the idea here is, again, we're just
fitting lines, but now we're fitting more
than one line.
And so the idea is, we have some intercept
terms, so that's
just the baseline level of, wage that we
might have, and then
we might have a, a relationship with the
age of the person,
and then we might have relationship with
what job class you're in.
So one way that we typically do that is,
by fitting an indicator variable.
So an indicator variable is a variable
that's denoted like this in mathematical
notation.
It just says, if the job class for the ith
person is equal to information, this
variable's equal to one.
If the job class for the ith person is not
equal to information, then
this information is equal to zero, and so
this represents the difference in the
wages between the people with job class
equal to information versus job class
equal
to not information, when you, fix all the
other variables in the regression model.
You can also do this for education it's a
little
bit more complicated road because there
are multiple education levels.
So we create an indicator variable for,
each of the different education
levels and so, here this is the sum of
four indicator variables.
And so the, the variable's equal to one,
if the education
for person I is equal to level K, that
variables equal to one and zero otherwise.
So then we can fit the model just like we
did before
so we have, we're using the train function
in the caret package.
And we again use wage as the outcome and
then tilde represents the formula
on the right, it's going to be used to
predict the variable on the left.
So we use age, job class, and education.
So job class and education are both factor
variables in r and so by
default it does, you know, it creates
these indicator variables like I've shown
here.
So, that when it fits the model it takes
that into account by automatically.
Again we're fitting the model on the
training set
and we can look at the final model and
you can see now that the final model has
ten predictors even though we only put
three variable
names into the formula and the reason is
because
this, variable right here, got, actually
received more than
one, predictor in the data set because of
the
way that we had to create these indicator
functions.
So then we can look at some diagnostic
plots.
So this is very typical for when you're
building these regression models.
The idea here is you can plot the fitted
values, so this is the predictions from
our model on
the training set versus the residuals,
that's the amount
of variation that's left over after you
fit your model.
And so what you'd like to see is that.
This line would be centered at zero on
this, axis because the residuals is the,
difference between our model prediction
and our,
actual real values that we're trying to
predict.
And here, you can see there's still a
couple of outliers
up here that have been labeled for you in
this plot.
And so, those variables might be variables
that we
want to try to explore a little bit
further and
see if we can identify any other
predictors in
our data set that might be able to explain
them.
The other thing that we can do is color by
variables not just used in the model.
So for example here I'm plotting again the
fitted values from our model versus the
residuals.
And so again, we like to see this laying
on the zero
line because it's the difference between
our fitted values and our real values.
And so, what we can do is plot on this
plot, we can again plot
it by different variables, in this case,
we can plot it by for example, race.
And so you can see that it seems like some
of these
outliers up here may be explained by the
race variable in the
data set and so these another exploratory
technique plotting the fitted model
versus the residuals then coloring it
by different variables to identify
potential trends.
Another thing that can be really useful
is plotting the fitted residuals versus
the index.
And what do I mean by the index?
So the data set comes in a set of rows
that you got in a particular order.
And so the index is just which row of the
data set you're looking at.
And the y axis here is the residuals.
And so you can see that all the residuals
seems to be happening, high residuals seem
to be happening down here at the right end
of the high, the highest row numbers.
And you can also see a trend with respect
to row numbers and so
whenever you can see a trend or a outlier
like that with respect to the
row numbers, it suggests that there's a
variable missing from your model because
you're
plotting the residuals here, so that's the
difference between the true values and the
fitted.
And that shouldn't have any relationship
to the order
in which the variables appear in your data
set.
Unless, and this is what's typically you
discover when you see
a trend like this, or outliers like this
at one end of
this plot, that there's a relationship
with respect to time, or
age, or some other continuous variable
that the rows are ordered by.
So the other thing that you can do is plot
the wage variable.
So this is the wage variable in the test
set versus the predicted values in the
test set.
So ideally these two things would be very
close to each other.
Ideally you'd have essentially a straight
line on the 45
degree line where wage was exactly equal
to our predictions.
Of course that isn't how it always works
out.
And then in the test set, you can explore
and try to identify trends that you might
have missed.
So, for example, here we're looking at the
year
that the data was collected in the test
set.
As a way of exploring how our model might
have broken down.
Now something to keep in mind is that if
you do
this sort of exploration in the test set,
you can't then
go back and re-update your model in the
training set because
that would be using the test set to
rebuild your predictors.
This is more like a post-mortem on your
analysis or a
way to try to determine whether your
analysis worked or not.
If you want all of the covariants in your
model building, one
thing that you can do is use this again in
the training function.
You can pass it an outcome and then tilde
and then if you put
a dot here instead of putting a set of
variables separated by plus signs.
It says predict with all of the variables
in the data set.
So, this is model fit with all of the
variables and
so this is the wage variable and the
predictions here and
so you can actually see that it does a
little bit
better when you include all of the
variables in the data set.
This is By default if you don't want to
try to do some sort of model selection in
advance.
So linear regression is often useful in
combination with other models.
It's a quite a simple model in the
sense that it always fits lines through
the data.
And so it can be, capture a lot of
variability
if the relationship between the predictors
and the outcome is linear.
If it's not linear, then you can often
miss
things, and it can be better blended with
other models.
We'll talk about model blending later in
the class.
Exploratory data analysis can be very
useful with regression
models because, like, the plots we made
with residuals
and so forth colored by different
features, you can
try to identify the patterns in the data
set.
There's more information in these three
books, if you want to
go and find a lot more about regression
modeling for prediction.