This lecture's about preprocessing
predictor variables.
And, so as we saw on previous lectures,
you need to plot the variables
upfront so you can see if there's any sort
of weird behavior of those variables.
And sometimes predictors will look very
strange
or the distribution will be very strange,
and
you might need to transform them in order
to make them more useful for prediction
algorithms.
This is particularly true when you're
using model based algorithms.
Like linear discriminate analysis, naive
Bayes,
linear regression and things like that.
We'll talk about all those methods later
in the
class, but just keep in mind that
pre-processing can
be more useful often when you're using
model based
approaches, then when you're using more
non parametric approaches.
So, why preprocess?
Here again I'm loading the later, the
caret package, and I'm
learning the kernlab package and then I'm
attaching the spam data.
Again just like I talked about previously,
when you're deciding how to preprocess
data, or how to explore data we only look
at the training set.
So, we split data right away into training
and testing
data and we set the testing data aside for
later.
Now if I look at one of the variables, so
again, this is spam data,
so we're trying to predict whether the
data is spam or if it's good emails, ham.
And, so the variables are things like how
many capitals do we see in a row?
What's the run length for the number of
capitals in a row in an email?
If you take, make a histogram of those
values, you see, for example,.
That almost all of the run links are very
small,
but there are a few that are much, much
larger.
This is an example of a variable that is
very skewed, and, so it's
very hard to deal with in model
based predictors and so you might want to
preProcess.
So, if you take the mean of this variable,
it's about 4.7.
But the standard deviation is huge, it's
much much larger.
So, it's much more highly variable
variable.
And so, what you might want to do is do
some sort of preprocessing, so
the machine learning algorithms don't get
tricked by
the fact that it's skewed and highly
variable.
So, one way that you can do this is by
basically standardizing variables, and the
usual way to standardize variables, is to
take the variable values, and subtract
their mean.
Then put, so you take the value, subtract
the mean,
and then divide that whole quantity by the
standard deviation.
When you do that the mean of the variables
that you have will be zero.
And the standard deviation will be one, so
that will
reduce a lot of that variability that we
saw previously.
And it will, standardize the variable
somewhat.
One thing to keep in mind is, again, when
we apply a prediction algorithm to the
test set.
We have to be aware that we can only
use parameters that we estimated in the
training set.
In other words, when we apply this same
standardization
to the test set, we have to use the
mean from the training set, and the
standard deviation
from the training set, to standardize the
testing set values.
What does this mean?
It means that when you do the
standardization, the
mean will not be exactly zero in the test
set.
And the standard deviation will not be
exactly one, because
we've standardized by parameters estimated
in the training set, but
hopefully they'll be close to those values
even though we're
using not the exact values built in the
test set.
You can also use the preProcess function
to do a lot of standardization for you.
So, the preprocess function is a function
that is built into the caret package.
And here I'm passing it all of
the training variables except for one,
except for
the 58th in the data set, which is the
actual outcome that we care about.
And I'm telling it to center every
variable and scale every variable.
That will do that same transformation that
we talked about previously to
the data, where you subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation.
And you can see that by looking at the
mean of the value capitalAve, just like we
did before.
And you can see that after using the
preProcess function
the mean is zero, and the standard
deviation is one.
So, preprocess can be used to perform a
lot of the preprocessing
tool, techniques that you, you used to
have to do by hand.
The other thing that you can do is you can
use the object that's created
using the preprocessing technique to apply
that same preprocessing to the test set.
So, here this preObj was the object used
on the previous slide.
That was the object that we created by
preprocessing the training set.
So, looking at that value we can see, now,
if we pass the testing set to the predict
function.
Then what it'll do is it will take
the values calculated on the preprocessing
object and apply
them to the test set object, and so again,
in the pre, post process test set data
the mean won't exactly be equal to zero
for any variable and the standard
deviation won't exactly
be equal to one, but they'll be close,
because we used the training set values to
normalize.
You can also pass the preprocessed
commands directly
to the train function in caret, as an
argument.
So, for example here we can send to the
preprocessed
argument of the train function, the
command, the parameters center
and scale, and that will center and scale
all of
the predictors, before using those
predictors in the prediction model.
The other thing that you can do is do
other kinds of transformation.
So, centering and scaling is one approach,
and that will take
care of some the problems that we see in
these data.
You can remove, very strongly biased
predictors
or predictors that have super high
variability.
The other thing that you can do is use
other
different kinds of transformations one
example is the box cox transforms.
Box cox transforms are a set of
transformations
that take continuous data, and try to make
them
look like normal data and they do that by
estimating a specific set of parameters
using maximum likelihood.
So, if I use the preprocess function and I
tell it to
perform box cox transformations on each of
the variables, and then I predict.
Each of the different variables using that
preprocess object on the training set.
I can look at the capital average values,
and I can make a histogram of those
values.
And now, remember in the original plot on
the histogram, they looked
like a huge pile at zero and a few values
that were large.
And now you see something that look a
little bit more like
a normal distribution, a little bit more
like a bell curve here.
You will notice that it doesn't take care
of all of the problems.
So, for example there's still a stack set
of values here at zero and
in the Q-Q plot, so this is
showing the theoretical quantiles of the
normal distribution.
Versus the sample quintiles that we
calculated for our
preProcess data, you can see that they
don't perfectly
line up and in particular there's this
again chunk
down here at the bottom these don't lie on
a perfect 45 degree line, and that's
because if
you have a bunch of values that are
exactly
equal to zero this is a continuous
transform and
it doesn't take care of values that are
repeated.
So, it doesn't take care of a lot of the
problems that
would happen, would occur with using a
variable that's highly skewed though.
So, the thing that we can do is also
impute data for these data sets.
So, it's very common to have missing data.
And when you're using missing data in
the data sets, the prediction algorithms
often fail.
Prediction algorithms are built not to
handle missing data in most cases.
So, if you have some missing data.
You can impute them using something called
k-nearest neighbor's imputation.
So here we set the seed again, because
this is
a randomized algorithm, and we want to get
reproducible results.
And I take just these capital average
values
and, I create a new variable called
CapAve.
Then I generate randomly a bunch of values
using the rbinom function
to set equal to NA and I set those values
to be missing.
So, now this variable capAve is exactly
like the capitalAve
valuable only it has a subset of values
that are missing.
So, now I want to know how would I handle
those missing values?
I did this so that we could see how we
could handle missing values in a dataset.
So, one thing that you going to do is you
going to get
news as preProcess function and tell it to
do k-nearest neighbors imputation.
K-nearest neighbors computation find the
k.
So if k equal to ten, then the 10
nearest, data vectors that look most like
data vector
with the missing value, and average the
values of
the variable that's missing and compute
them at that position.
So, if we do that, then we can predict on
our training set, all of
the new values, including the ones that
have been imputed with the k-nearest
imputation algorithm.
We can then standardize those values,
using the same standardization procedure
that we
did before, by subtracting the mean and
divided by the standard dev, deviation.
One thing you can do is you can look at
the comparison between the
actual, in this case, when we set some of
the values to be equal
to NA in advance, we can look at the
values that were imputed, and
the values that were truly there before we
removed them and made them NAs.
And we can see how close those two values
are to each other.
And so, you can see, for example, that.
Those values are relatively close to each
other.
Most of the differences are very close to
zero.
Here you can see the values are mostly
very close to zero.
So the imputation work relatively well.
You can also do look at just the values
that were imputed.
So again here I'm looking at a capAve
quantile of the same difference between
the imputed values.
And the true values, they're only for the
ones that were missing.
And here you can see again, most of the
values are close to zero, but here we're
only looking at the ones we're missing, so
clearly some of them are more variable
than previously.
And then you can look at the ones that
were not the ones that we selected to be
NA.
And you can see that they're even closer
to each other, and
so the ones that got imputed are a little
bit further apart.
But aren't that much further apart.
So, there is a lot more to learn
about training and testing sets in terms
of transformations.
But train, but the things to keep in mind
are that
training in test sets must be processed in
the same way.
The caret package handles a lot of this
under the hood in
the sense that if you train a data set
using preProcess functions.
Built into the train function and caret
way
it applies that preprocessed function to
the test set.
It will handle all of the preprocessing in
the correct way for you.
In general, you need to pay attention to
the
fact that anything you do to the training
set.
Will create a set of parameters.
You must use only those parameters when
you apply it to the test set.
You can't estimate new transformations on
the test set alone.
And that means that the test set
transformations will likely be imperfect.
Especially if the test and training sets
are
diff, collected at different times or in
different ways.
Some of the transformations won't
necessarily work as well.
All of the tra, transformations I'm
talking about, so
far other than imputation are based on
continuous variables.
When dealing with factor variables it's a
little
bit more difficult to know what's the
right transformation.
Most machine learning algorithms are built
to deal with either
binary predictors, in which the binary
predictors are not pre-processed.
Or continuous predictors in which case
sometimes it's expected
that, the data are preprocessed to look
more normal.
You can go to this link that I've linked
here to look, into
more information about how to preProcess
data for prediction using the caret
package.