This lecture is about predicting with
trees.
The basic idea is that if you have a
bunch of variables that you want to use to
predict
an outcome, you can take each of those
variables,
and use it to split the outcome into
different groups.
And, so as you split the outcomes into
different groups, then
you can evaluate the homogeneity of the
outcome within each group.
And continue to split again if necessary,
and
then, until you get outcomes that are
separated
into groups that are homogeneous enough,
or that
they are small enough that you need to
stop.
The pros of this approach are that it's
easy
to interpret right, and you tend to get
better
performance in non-linear settings than
you do with the
linear regression models we talked about
in the previous lectures.
The cons are that without precluding or
some
kind of cross-validation, this can lead to
overfitting.
And they can be harder to estimate
uncertainty than
it can be for the linear regression model
setting.
In general the results may be variable
depending on exact
values of the parameters, or the variables
that you collected.
So here's an example of what a decision
tree looks like after it has already been
built.
So this is a decision tree that appeared
in the New York Times during the 2008
elections, when Bar, Barack Obama was
running against
Hillary Clinton for the Democratic
nomination for President.
And they were trying to decide what would
be a prediction rule
for whether a county would vote for Obama
or for Hillary Clinton.
And, so the way that happened was that
they would, build a prediction model that
would ask questions of each of the
different
variables that they had in their data set.
So the best split happened to be this
variable.
So if the county was more than 20% African
American, then
the county was much more likely to vote
for, Barack Obama.
If it was less than 20% African American,
then it
became more likely that the county would
vote for Hilary Clinton.
Then within each of these two subgroups,
they went and
looked for other variables that might
split those subgroups out.
So, on this branch here, the next question
was,
is the high school graduation rate greater
than 78%?
If it wasn't, then the county was more
likely to vote for Hillary
Clinton, and if it was, then it's more
likely to vote for Barack Obama.
And the algorithm continues in that manner
until you've split out
into smallest, the smallest subgroups that
you are willing to consider.
And, so you see that within each of these
leaves of the tree, the predictions were
quite homogeneous.
In other words.
Obama was 383 out of about 450 counties in
this case.
And Hilary Clinton won 704 out of about
790 or 800 counties in this ca, case.
In other words, these questions split the
counties into groups that were homogenous
within each
leaf their prediction was likely to come
true
that, that candidate would win in the
election.
So the basic algorithm behind building one
of these trees
is, start with all the variables of one
big group.
And then, you find the first variable that
best splits the outcomes into two
different homogenous groups.
You then divided the data into two groups
which we call leaves,
and on, and the split that you just
performed is called a node.
Within each split, we then search through
all the variables, again.
Including the variable we just split on.
And try to find within that group if
there's another variable
or split that separates the outcome, into
even more homogeneous groups.
You continue until the groups are too
small, or they're sufficiently pure.
In other words, sufficiently homogeneous.
To, stop the algorithm.
So there are different measures of
impurity.
And they're all based on basically this
probability that you can estimate.
So, within a particular group.
So, in the le, m, m leaf then you have n
total objects that you might consider,
and you can count the number of times that
a particular class appears in that leaf.
So this is the number of times that class
k appears in leaf m.
So that's this probability.
So it's p hat for the mth leaf and the kth
class.
The misclassification error is 1 minus the
probability that you're
equal to the most common class in that
particular leaf.
So for example, if you're if it's a leaf
where.
Almost all of the counties would vote for
Barack Obama, then 1 minus the
misclassification error is
1 minus the er the misclassification error
is 1
minus the probability that you'd vote for
Barack Obama.
So zero means perfect purity.
In other words, there's no
misclassification error and
all of the counties would go for Barack
Obama.
0.5 means no purity because, it, it's not
one,
because in any particular leaf if the,
counties was overwhelming,
the counties where overwhelming likely to
vote for Hilary Clinton
then you would get perfect purity in the
other direction.
So it's actually when the leaf is
perfectly balanced between the two
different outcomes, that's when you don't
have homogeneity within that particular
leaf.
Similarly there's something called the
Gini index which is
not to be confused with the Gini
coefficient in economics,.
And it's basically 1 minus the sum of the
squared
probabilities that you belong to any of
the different classes.
So again zero means perfect purity.
In other words the class has one
particular class has probability equal
to 1 and all the other classes have
probability equal to 0.
0.5 means no purity.
In other words, all of the classes are
perfectly balanced within each leaf.
Deviance and information gain is another
measure that can be used, and so, it's
called deviance if you use log with base e
here, and log base 2 is information gain.
And it's basically minus the sum of the
probability.
Of being assigned to class k and leaf m
times
the log base 2 or base e, of that same
probability.
Value of zero means there is perfect
purity within
the leaf, and value of one means there's
no purity.
If you go to this link from Wikipedia,
you'll have a lot more information about
how these measures of impurity are used to
separate the, the values within each leaf.
So here's what they look like for a
couple, for an s, for a specific example.
So suppose we had a variable that was
trying to
split the dots into the blue and the red
dots.
If the variable splitting in the following
way were 15 of the dots were blue
in a particular leaf and only one was red,
that would be a relatively pure situation.
And so, misclassification rate would be
one out
of 16, so that's just this one dot here.
And so it's relatively low value the GinI
coefficient would also
be low, because it's one minus 1 divided
by 16 squared
plus 15 divided 16 squared which is a
relatively small number
and then the information gained is
similarly would be, in this case.
&Uh, smaller towards 0, because it's 1
over 16 times log base 2,
1 over 16 plus 15 divided by 16 times log
base 2 15 over 16.
So that's the case where there is
relatively pure outcome in the two groups.
We can also look at the case where it's
not.
So suppose this variable split the
outcomes into a leaf where half
of the values were blue, and half of the
values were red.
So that wouldn't be a very good split,
because it's basically a
coin flip whether you're from one class to
the other in that leaf.
And so then this classification right here
is .5, it's very large.
The Gini index is also maximized, it's .5,
and the information is also large, it's
one.
So, this would be a split that wouldn't be
made, because
it wouldn't separate the two groups very
well on that particular leaf.
So I'm just going to show you an example
with the iris data.
This is a very old data set, but it shows
you the idea of how this works.
So, this, I'm loading the data with the
command data iris.
And then I'm loading the ggplot2 library
for making plots.
So the names of this data set are the
different variables that we're going to be
using to predict with.
Here it's sepal length, Sepal.Width,
Petal.Length and Petal.Width
and what we're trying to predict is the
Species.
So there's 50 of these three different
species
that we're trying to predict with those
variables.
So again I always separate the data into
the training and the test set, and in this
case I have 45 examples in my training set
that I can use to build a prediction
model.
And the first thing that I do is, I'm
going to plot the petal width versus the
sepal width.
So that's petal width on the x axis, the
sepal width on the y axis, and then I'm
going to color it by the different
species, and you
can see there are three very distinct
clusters here.
So, it's a relatively easy classification
problem.
It might be a little bit challenging for a
linear model,
but not necessarily challenging for this
more advanced model with classification
trace.
So you can fit the model using the train
function in caret.
So again, I'm training the model.
The outcome is species.
I'm predicting with all the remaining
variables, which is
why I have this tilde and then a dot.
And I'm telling it the method is rpart
which is [UNKNOWN]
package for doing regression and
classification trees, one of the packages.
And I'm telling you to use the training
data.
If I look at the final model, it tells me
what all the nodes are and how they're
split and in order to, and what the the
probability of being in each class is for
each split.
So, here for example, there's a split that
says petal.length is less
than 2.45, and if that happens then you in
that case all of the
examples that have pedal length less than
2.45 belong to this bc setosa.
So, you can read those model splits to
tell you, what the classification tree is
doing.
You can also make a plot of the
classification tree.
And so if you just, plot the final model
that's produce what
it will do is it will produce what's
called a dandergram, like this.
And so it's a little hard to read, it's
cut
off here, but you can see petal length
less than 2.45.
Then you're assigned a setosa.
And so you can follow to the left what
happens if the petal length is
less than 2.45, and to the right what
happens if petal length isn't less than
2.45.
And then follow the next split here at
this node
down to the, see the total classification
for any particular example.
A prettier version of that plot can be
made with the rattle package.
So, you use the function fancyRpartPlot,
and you pass
it the final model that was fit using
caret.
And it makes again dentigram, but now it's
a
little bit easier to see, so here we see.
That if the petal length is less than 2.5,
we move over here to the
left, and if it's greater than 2.5 then we
go over here to the right.
And then, within that split, so once
you've already made that
decision about those samples, and if the
petal length is less
that 4.8 you go down here to the left, and
if
the petal length is greater you go over
here to the right.
And so this makes it a little bit easier
to see what's going on.
You can predict new values using the
predict function,
just like you can with the other linear
regression models.
Here the prediction is going to be a
particular class label,
because the classification tree was built
to predict a particular class.
And, so when I pass the new data, testing
data, to the model.
It'll actually write out the different
categories of species,
because it's actually predicting the class
for each variable.
So notes and further resources,
classification trees
are non-linear models, so they immediately
use
interactions between variables, this is
important to
keep in mind, because it's always a
model that's built on the relationship
between
multiple variables and if you have a
large number of classes for a particular
variable for example that you're
predicting with.
The models can over-fit a little bit.
The data transformations may be a little
bit less important.
If you do any monotone transformation of
a continuous variable, in other words, any
transformation
that doesn't change the order of the
values, but maybe makes them bigger or
smaller.
Then you will get the same data
splits, with the classification or
regression trees.
This can make the transformations a little
bit less important.
They can also be used for regression
problems.
So, I showed measures of misclassifcation
impurity, you can also
use root mean squared error as a measure
of impurity.
And do a similar classification tree
building
procedure for building models for
regression as well.
There are multiple tree building options
in RR, both in
the caret package, using the party
package, the rpart package.
Or you can even use this package tree
which doesn't appear in the caret package,
but
I also has a lot of use, useful
functions that can be used when building
these models.
For more information you can read in, in
these two books,
where there's a lot of good information
about classification and regression trees.
Or, in this book about, that's more
specifically targeted to this particular
prediction algorithm.