This lecture is about bagging, which is
short for bootstrap aggregating.
The basic idea is that when you fit
complicated models,
sometimes if you average those models
together, you get a
smoother model fit, that gives you a
better balance between
potential bias in your fit and variance in
your fit.
So bootstrap aggregating has a very simple
idea.
The basic idea is take your data and take
resamples of the data set.
So, this is the similar to the idea of
bootstrapping, which you would have
learned about in the inference class that
is part of the data science
specialization.
After you resample the cases with
replacement, then
you recalculate your prediction function
on that resampled data.
And then you either average the
predictions from all these repeated
predictors that
you built or you majority vote or
something like that when you're doing
classification.
The thing is that you get a similar bias
that you would get from fitting any one
of those models individually, but a
reduced variability
because you've averaged a bunch of
different predictors together.
This is most useful for non-linear
functions.
So, we'll show an example with smoothing,
but it's
also very useful for things like
predicting with trees.
So I'm going to go back to the ozone data,
so it's in the ElemStatLearn package.
And I load the the ozone data set.
I then order for the purposes of showing
you how this works,
I'm going to order the data set by the
outcome, the ozone variable here.
And then I look at the data set and I
can see it has four variables, ozone,
radiation, temperature, and wind.
So the idea is that I'm going to try
to predict temperature as a function of
ozone.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the first thing that we can do is just
show you an example of how this works.
So the basic idea is, I'm going to create
a matrix
here and it's going to have 10 rows and a
155 columns.
Then what I'm going to do is, I'm going to
resample the data set.
In for ten different times, so then a
loop over ten different samples of the
data set.
Each time I'm going to sample width
replacement from the entire data set.
Then I'm going to create a new data set,
ozone0, which is
the resample data set for that particular
element of the loop.
And that's just the subset of the data set
corresponding to our random sample.
Then I'm going to reorder the data set
every time by
the ozone variable, and you'll see why in
just a minute.
Then I fit a loess curve each time, so a
loess is
kind of a smooth curve that you can fit
through the data.
It's very similar to the sublime model
fits that we
saw in a previous example with modeling
with linear regression.
And so the basic idea is we're fitting
a smooth curve relating temperature, to
the ozone variables.
So temperature is the outcome, and ozone
is the predictor, and each time I
use the resample data set as the data set
I'm building that predictor on.
And I use a common span for each time, the
span being a measure of how smooth that
fit will be.
I then predict for every single loess
curve the outcome
for a new data set for the exact same
values.
I always predict for ozone values 1 to
155.
So the ith row of this ll object is now
the prediction from
the loess curve, from the ith resample of
the date ozone.
So what I've done here?
I've resampled my data set ten different
times, fit a smooth curve through it those
ten different times, and then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to average those
values.
So, here's what it looks like in this
plot.
So, here I've plotted ozone on the x
axis, these are the observed ozone values
versus temperature
on the y axis, those are the observed
temperature values, and each black dot
represents an observation.
Each gray line here represents the fit
with one resampled data set.
So you can see the gray lines that have a
lot of curviness to them.
They capture a lot of the variability in
the data set.
But they also maybe over-capture some of
the variability.
They're little bit too curvy.
Once I've averaged those lines together I
get something that's a little
bit smoother and is closer to the middle
of the data set.
That's the red line.
So the red line is the bagged loess curve.
It's basically the average of multiple
fitted loess curves,
the same data set where I've resampled it
every time.
There's a proof that shows that the
bagging estimate will always have
lower variability but similar bias to the
individual model fits that you do.
In the caret package there's some models
that already perform bagging for you.
So if you're using the train function you
could set method to be bagEarth, treebag,
or bagFDA.
And those are specific bagged models that
the the
model that the caret package will fit for
you.
Alternatively, you can actually build your
own bagging function in caret.
This is a bit of an advanced use and so I
recommend that you
read the documentation carefully if you're
going to be trying to do that yourself.
The idea here though is you basically are
going to
take your predictor variable and put it
into one data frame.
So I'm going to make the predictors be a
data frame that contains the ozone data.
Then you have your outcome variable.
Here's it's going to be just a temperature
variable from the data set.
And I pass this to the bag function in
caret package.
So I tell it, I want to use the predictors
from that data frame, this is my outcome,
this
is the number of replications with the
number of
sub samples I'd like to take from the data
set.
And then bagControl tells me something
about how I'm going to fit the model.
So fit is the function that's going to be
applied to fit the model every time.
This could be a call to the train function
in the caret package.
Predict is a the way that given a
particular
model fit, that we'll be able to predict
new values.
So this could be, for example, a call to
the predict function from a trained model.
And then aggregate is the way that we'll
put the var, the predictions together.
So for example it could average the
predictions across all the different
replicated samples.
You can see that if you look at this
custom bag version of the conditional
regression trees, you can
see that it gets some of the benefit that
I
was showing you in the previous slide with
bag loess.
So the idea here is I'm plotting ozone
again on the x-axis versus temperature on
the y-axis.
The little grey dots represent actual
observed values.
The red dots represent the fit from a
single conditional regression tree.
And so you can see that for example, it
capture, it doesn't capture the
trend that's going on down here very well,
the red line is just flat.
Even though there appears to be a trend
upward in the data points here.
But when I average over ten different
bagged
model model fits with these conditional
regression trees.
I see that there's an increase here in the
values in
the blue fit, which is the fit from the
bagged regression.
So we're going to look a little bit
at those different parts of the bagging
function.
So in this particular case I'm using the
ctreeBag function, which you
can look at in, if you've loaded the caret
package in R.
So, for the fit part it takes the data
frame
that we've passed and the predict, and the
outcome that
we've passed, and it basically uses the
ctree function to
train a tree, conditional regression tree
on the data set.
This is the last command that's called the
ctree command.
So it returns this model fit from the
ctree function.
The prediction takes in the object.
So this is going to be an object from the
ctree model fit.
And a new data set x, and it's going to
get a new prediction.
So what you can see here is it basically
calculates each time
the tree response or the outcome from the
object and the new data.
It then calculates this probability matrix
and
returns either the actually the observed
levels that
it predicts or it actually re, just
returns
the response, the predicted response from
the variable.
The aggregation then takes those values
and averages
them together or puts them together in
some way.
So here what this is doing is
it's basically getting the prediction from
every
single one of these model fits, so that' s
across a large number of observations.
And then it binds them together into one
data matrix by with
each row being equal to the prediction
from one of the model predictions.
And then it takes the median at every
value.
So in other words it takes the median
prediction from
each of the different model fits across
all the bootstrap samples.
So bagging is very useful for nonlinear
models, and it's widely used.
It's often used with trees.
And you can think of an extension to this
as
being random forest, which we'll talk
about in a future lecture.
Several models use bagging and caret's
main train
function, like I told you about in
previous slide.
And you can also build your own specific
bagging functions, for any
classification or prediction algorithm
that you'd like to take a look at.
For further resources, I've linked to a
couple
of different tutorials on bagging and
boosting, as
well as the Elements of Statistical
Learning which
has a lot more details about how bagging
works.
But remember that the basic idea is to
basically resample
your data, refit your nonlinear model,
then average those model
fits together over resamples to get a
smoother model fit,
than you would've got from any individual
fit on its own