This lecture's about model based
prediction.
The basic idea here is that we're going to
assume the data follow a specific
probabilistic model.
Then we're going to use base therom to
identify optimal classifiers based on that
probabilistic model.
The advantage is that this approach can
take advantage
of some structure that might appear in the
data.
For example the fall of distribution.
And that may lead to some computational
conveniences.
There may also be reasonable accurate
on real problems, particularly the real
problems
that appear to follow the data
distribution
that under lies our whole holistic model.
The cons are that they do make
these additional assumptions about the
data, and they
don't have to be exactly satisfied in
order
for the prediction algorithms to work very
well.
But if they're very far off, the
algorithms may fail.
And when the model is incorrect, you do
get reduced accuracy.
So
here's the model based approach.
Our goal is to build a parametric
model, or a model based on probability
distributions.
For the conditional distribution the
probability that y
our outcome equals some specific class k
given
a particular set of predictor variables so
that
our x variables equal the little value of
x.
A typical approach is to apply a Bayes
theorem.
In other words we want to know something
about the probability y equals
k that y comes from class k given the
variables that we've observed.
And we write that down using Bay's theorem
as the probability X equals X given Y
equals K times the probability Y equals K
divided by the law of total probability
here below.
If you don't remember Bay's theorem from
your inference class in data
science specialization you can go and read
about it was this Wikipedia page.
We then assume some parametric model for
the distribution
of the features given the class, so that's
this component
here at sub k of x and we assume a
prior that each particular element comes
from a specific class.
That's denoted here by this pi sub k.
So then we can basically model the
distribution, the probability
that y equals k given a particular set of
predictor
variables as, this, fraction here where we
have a model
for the x variables and a model for the
prior probability.
The prior probabilities, pi k, are usually
set in advance from the data.
And then a common choice for fk of x is a
Gaussian distribution.
It may be a multivariate Gaussian
distribution if there are multiple x
variables.
And then we might estimate the parameters,
mu k and sigma squared k, from the data.
Then once we have these parameters
estimated, we can calculate the
probability y
belongs to any given class, as soon as we
observe the predictor variables.
And we classify the variables to the
class having the highest probability in
this sense.
So, a range of models use this approach.
The most popular of which is probably
linear discriminant analysis,
which assumes that 'f' 'k' of 'x' is a
multivariate Gaussian
Distribution, so the features have
a multivariate Gaussian Distribution
within each
class and there is the same covariance
matrix for every class.
This ends up drawing basically lines
through the data, the covariate space.
And so that's why it's called linear
discriminant analysis, we'll see that in a
minute.
Quadratic discriminant analysis is very
much like linear discriminant analysis,
although
it allows different covariance matrices
within each of the different classes.
And so that ends up drawing quadratic
curves through the data, as opposed to
lines.
Model base prediction basically allows for
more complicated
versions of the covariance matrix when
building these models.
And naive Bayes classifiers, which we'll
talk about a little
bit more in this lecture, basically assume
independence between the features.
So, in other words in, assume independence
between
our predictor variables through the model
building process.
This may not be true.
We may not believe the features are or the
predictors are
independent, but it still might be a
useful model for prediction purposes.
So, why is this called linear discriminant
analysis?
Well, if we consider the ratio of the
probabilities of the two classes.
So, this is the probability you're in
class K.
Given our predictor variables, divided by
the probability
here in class j given the predictor
variables.
And we take the log of that quantity, so
if we
take the log of it, it's a monotone
function which means that.
As this ration increases, so will the log
of that ratio.
So we can look at this quantity, and we
can see that
that breaks down by basically writing
these quantities out using base theorem.
As on the previous page, we get log of the
ratio of the two Gaussian densities.
Plus log of the ratio of the two prior
probabilities.
Now these terms are actually require more
writing so can write
them out and we end up with this term goes
here.
We get the log of the [UNKNOWN] ratio of
the prior probabilities.
Plus a term here that depends on the
parameters of
our Gaussian distributions or are normal
distributions for each class.
Plus a linear term, so this a, an
x variable here times one coefficient here
which
is a linear terms so you end up
getting basically lines that are drawn
through the data.
And a variable will have a higher
probability of
one class if it's on one side of the
line and a higher probability of being in
another
class if it's on the other side of the
line.
If this flew by your head a little too
fast, don't
worry about that too much but you can go
and read
about it more carefully in the elements of
statistical learning if
you'd like to know a little bit more about
those details.
So this is what the decision boundaries
tend to
look at, like, for these sort of
prediction models.
So imagine we have three different groups
of, points.
So we're trying to classify into class
one, class two or class three.
And we have two variables that we're using
to
classify and that's the x and the y axis
here.
What would end up, what we would
end up doing is fitting one Gaussian
distribution.
Here's one Gaussian distribution.
Here's another Gaussian distribution.
And here's a third Gaussian distribution.
So one to each class.
And then we would basically draw lines
where the probability switches over from
being.
Higher in this class to that class.
So, that ends up looking like lines like
this.
So, if you're on this side of the line,
you'll be classified as a two.
If you're on this side of the line, you'll
be classified as a three.
And if you're down here, you'll be
classified as a one.
So this basically is how it works.
You basically fit Gaussian distributions
to the data and then use those Gaussian
distributions to draw lines that, assign
the
prop points to the highest posterior
probabilities.
In general, the discriminate function is
what gets used here.
So the basic idea is we have a
discriminate function that looks like this
where u, uk is the mean of class K for all
our features.
Sigma inverse is the inverse of the
co-variance matrix for that class.
Actually, it's the same in co-variance
matrix for all classes here.
And then this is the term, the linear term
in x,
the predictors that we have, and our
co-variance matrix and the mean.
And so basically what we do is we plug in
our new data value into this function.
And we pick the value of k that
produces the largest value of this
particular discriminate function.
And that's we how we decide on a class.
You can usually estimate these parameters
by maximum likelihood estimation.
If you remember that from the inference
that you
would've taken as part of the data science
specialization.
Now e base does something a little bit
more to more to simplify the problem.
So, again, suppose now we're trying to
model the
probability that y is in a particular
class, k.
And we have a bunch of variables that we
want to predict with.
We can use Bayes' theorem to say the
probability that the
class is K given all these variables that
we've observed is
the prior probability we're in class k
times the probability for
all these features given you're in class k
divided by some constant.
So the way that this can be written is
that this probability is proportional to.
The prior probability times the
probability of
the features, given that we're in class K.
In other words, if you picked the largest
value of this quantity
here, it will be the same as picking the
largest probability here.
Because the term in the denominator is
just a constant for all the different
probabilities.
We can then break that down a little bit
further.
We can say the probability of the features
and the class variable k is equal to this
prior probability times the probability of
x one given here in class k.
Times the probability of the, all the
other
variables except for X1, conditional on Xi
and YK.
So this is basically just a statement
about probability that you
might remember from your inference class
and the data science specialization.
You can continue to break down in the same
way until you get one term for every
feature.
But those features are always conditional
on all the
other variables that you, that have come
before it.
And so that's basically because each
features may, or
each of the predictors may be dependent on
each other.
One assumption you could make to make this
quite a bit easier would be
to just assume that all of the predictor
variables are independent of each other.
In which case they drop out of this
conditioning argument.
And you end up with the prior probability
times the probability
of each feature by itself conditional on
being in each class.
Now this is kind of a naive assumption
because we're assuming that
all the features are independent even
though we know they're probably not.
And that's why this method has the title
Naive Bayes.
And so, it still works reasonably well in
a large number of applications.
And it's particularly useful when you have
a very large
number of features that are, binary or
are, categorical variables.
This very frequently get, comes up in.
Text classification and classification of
other kind of document classification.
So just to show you briefly how these two
work we're,
I'm going to show you on the Iris Data
again and I'm going to
load ggplot2 library, I've got these
variable I'm using to predict and
I again have these, three different
species that I'm trying to predict.
And I can fit them, on a training set and
apply them to a test set.
Just like I do with all of our other
prediction algorithms.
So, I again use the create data partition.
Create a training set.
And a test set.
I can then build an lda model on the
training set, in the following way.
I just basically use the train function
from the cara package.
I pass it the training set, and I tell it
method lda.
And then I can do similarly for naive
base, and nb
is the method that we pass for, a naive
base classification.
And I can predict the values from lda and
from a naive
base on the test set and make a table of
the predictions.
And we can see that the predictions agree
for all but one value.
So even though we know that the features
or the predictors are dependent here,.
Using the naive based classification means
very
similar prediction rules to the linear
discriminate analysis
classification and so we can do a
comparison
of the results and we see that just
this one value the value that appears
right
here between the two classes appears to be
not classified in the same way by the
two outputs but overall they perform very
similarly.
You can learn more about nieve based
classification and other model based
classification in the introduction to
statistical
learning and elements of statistical
learning books.
You can also learn about model based
clustering in
more detail in this academic paper that
I've linked to.
And the linear discriminant analysis
and quadratic discriminant analysis
Wikipedia pages.
Are also quite good and useful for,
Reference.