This lecture is about random forests,
which you can think
of as an extension to bagging for
classification and regression trees.
The basic idea is very similar to bagging
in the sense that we bootstrap
samples, so we take a resample of our
observed data, and our training data set.
And then we rebuild classification or
regression
trees on each of those bootstrap samples.
The one difference is that at each split,
when we split the
data each time in a classification tree,
we also bootstrap the variables.
In other words, only a subset of
the variables is considered at each
potential split.
This makes for a diverse set of potential
trees that can be built.
And so the idea is we grow a large number
of trees.
And then we either vote or average those
trees
in order to get the prediction for a new
outcome.
The pros for this approach are that it's
quite accurate.
And along with boosting, it's one of the
most, widely
used and highly accurate methods for
prediction in competitions like Kaggle.
The cons are that it's, it can be quite
slow.
It has to build a large number of trees.
And it can be hard to interpret, in the
sense that
you might have a large number of trees
that are averaged together.
And those trees represent bootstrap
samples with bootstrap nodes
that can be a little bit complicated to
understand.
It can also lead to a little bit of
overfitting
which can be complicated by the fact that
it's very hard
to understand which trees are leading to
that overfitting, and so
it's very important to use cross
validation when building random forests.
Here's an example of how this works in
practice.
So the idea is that you build a large
number
of trees where each tree is based on a
bootstrap sample.
So, for example, this tree is built on a
random subsample of your data and this is
a separate random subsample of the data
and
this is a separate random subsample of the
data.
And then at each node we allow a different
subset of the variables to potentially
contribute to the splits.
Then if we get a new observation, say
this V observation here, we run that
observation through
tree one, and it ends up at this leaf down
here at the bottom of that, tree.
And so it gets a particular prediction
here.
Then the next, we take that same
observation,
we run it through the next tree, and
it goes down a slightly different leaf,
and
it gets a slightly different set of
predictions here.
And finally we go down the third tree,
and we get an even different set of
predictions.
Then what we do is we basically average
those predictions together in order
to get the predictive probabilities of
each class across all the different trees.
So I'm going to show you an example of how
this works.
I'm going to load the iris data in and I'm
going to use the ggplot2 package for
showing some plots.
I'm going to build a training set and a
test set
again building the data set only on the
training set.
In the caret package, I use the train
function
just like I've used for the other model
building.
I send it the training data set and I tell
it method equals rf, which is the random
forest method.
I'm also telling it to fit the outcome to
be Species
and to use any of the other predictive
variables as potential predictors.
I'm setting prox equals true.
You'll see why I'm doing that in a minute
because it produces a little bit of extra
information.
And then I could use when I'm building
these model fits.
So here it tells me that I built the model
and I've
done bootstrap re-sampling and then, I
tried a bunch of different tuning
parameters.
And so the tuning parameter in particular
is the number of
basically tries, or number of repeated
trees that it's going to build.
I can look at a specific tree in our final
model fit using the get tree function.
So I applied get tree here to our final
model and I say I want the second tree
out.
And this is what the tree looks like.
So each of these columns, or each of these
rows corresponds to a particular split.
And so, you can see what the left daughter
of the
tree is, the right daughter of the tree,
which variable we're splitting
on, what's the value where that variable
is split and then
what the prediction is going to be out of
that particular split.
You can use this centers information as
well to see what
the predictions would be, or the center of
the class predictions.
So what I've done here is, I'm looking at
two particular variables.
The petal length and the petal width.
So I plotted petal width on the X axis and
petal length on the Y axis.
I then get the class centers.
So these are going to be the centers for
the predicted values.
So I'm going to send in the model fit, and
I'm going to give
it this prox variable which we asked for
in the previous fitting.
And when I'm going to tell it we're
looking at the training data set.
And so that gives us the class centers.
Those class centers will then, we can then
plot
those to see where they fall in the data.
So now, I've created the centers data set,
as well as the species data set.
And what I'm going to do is plot petal
width versus petal length.
And I'm going to color it by species in
the training data.
That's what I did with this qplot command.
Then I'm going to add points on top of
that.
That are the petal width and petal length,
corresponding to the color being the
species, and now I am using it from the
irsP which is the centers of the data set.
So what you can see is each dot here
represents an observation.
And the x's show the color center, or
the observation centers for each of the
different predictions.
So you can see that we predict the, each
species has a prediction for these two
variables that's right in the center of
the
cloud of points corresponding to that
particular species.
You can then predict new values using the
predict functions.
So you past to predict our model fit and
the testing data set.
And here, I'm also setting a variable,
testing predict right, which
is that we got the prediction right in the
data set.
In other words, our prediction is equal to
the testing data set species.
I can then make a table of our predictions
versus
the species to see what that variable
would look like.
So I can see for example I missed two
values here with my random forest model.
But overall [INAUDIBLE] it was highly
accurate in the prediction.
I can then look and see which of the two
that I missed.
And perhaps unsurprisingly you can see the
two that I missed,
marked in red here, are the two that,
in-between, two separate classes.
So remember there was one class up in this
right corner, and one class right here in
the middle, and this cloud, and the two
points
that lie right on the border we were
misclassified.
So you can kind of use this to explore,
and see where
your prediction is doing well and where
your prediction is doing poorly.
Random forests are usually one of the top
performing algorithms along with boosting
in any prediction contests.
They're often difficult to interpret
because of these multiple trees that we're
fitting but they can be very accurate for
a wide range of problems.
You can check out the rfcv function to
make sure that cross validation
is being performed, but the train function
in caret also handles that for you.
For more information you can read about
random forests directly from the inventor
here.
The Wikipedia page for random forests is
also quite good,
and the elements of statistical learning
covers it as well.