This lecture is about Boosting, which
along with random forest, is one
of the most accurate out of the box
classifiers that you can use.
The basic idea here is, take a large
number
of possibly weak predictors, and we're
going to take those
possibly weak predictors, and weight them
in a way,
that takes advantage of their strengths,
and add them up.
When we weight them and add them up, we're
sort of doing
the same kind of idea that we did with
bagging for regression trees.
Or that we did with random forest, where
we're talking
a large number of classifiers and sort of
averaging them.
And then, by averaging them together, we
get a stronger predictor.
So the basic idea here is to take k
classifiers.
These come from, usually, from the same
kind of class of classifiers.
And so, some ideas might be using all
possible classification trees, or all
possible regression models.
Or all possible cutoffs, where you just.
Divide the data into different points.
You then create a classifier that combines
these classification functions together,
and weights them together.
So, alpha sub t here is a weight times the
classifier ht of x, and so this weighted
set of classifiers, gives you a prediction
for the new point, that's our f of x.
The goal here is to minimize error on the
training set.
And so this is iterative at each step we
take, exactly one h.
We calculate weights for the next step,
based on
the errors that we get from that original
h.
And then we upweight missed
classifications, and
select the next stage and move on.
The most famous boosting algorithm is
probably Adaboost,
and here you can read about it on
Wikipedia.
You can also read this very nice tutorial
on boosting here, that will
also give us some of the material for the
rest of these lecture notes.
So, here's a really simple example.
Suppose we're trying to separate the blue
plus signs, from the
red minus signs, and we have two variables
to predict with.
So here I plotted variable one on the
x-axis, and variable two on the y-axis.
We haven't named them because this is just
a very simple example.
And so the idea is, can we build
a classifier that separates these
variables from each other?
We could start off with a really simple
classifier.
We could say just draw a line a vertical
line, and say, which vertical line
separates these points well?
Here's a, a classifier that says anything
to the left
of this vertical line is a blue plus, and
anything to
the right is a red minus, and so you can
see
we've misclassified these three points up
here in the top right.
So the thing that we would do is build
that classifier, calculate
the error rate, in this case we're missing
about 30% of the points.
And then we would upweight those points
that we missed.
Here I've shown that upweighting, by
drawing them in a larger scale.
So those pluses are now upweighted, for
building the next classifier.
We would then build the next classifier.
And in this case, our second classifier
would be,
one that drew a vertical line right over
here.
And so, that vertical line would classify
everything to
the right of that line as a red minus.
And everything to the left, as a blue
plus.
And so here we again, misclassified three
points, these three right here.
And so, those three points are now
upweighted, and
they are also drawn larger for the next
iteration.
So we can again calculate the error rate,
and
use that to calculate the weights for the
next step.
Then the third classifier, will
intentionally try to classify those
points that we misclassified in the last
couple of rounds.
So, for example, these pluses, and these
minuses need to be correctly classified.
To do that we now draw a horizontal line,
and we say anything below that horizontal
line is a
red minus, anything above is a blue plus,
and now
we misclassify this point, and these two
points over here.
So then what we can do, is we can take
that,
those classifiers, and we can weight them,
and add them up,
and so what we do is we say, we're
going to classify
a weighted combination of 0.42 times the
ver, the first vertical line.
Plus 0.65 times the second vertical line,
plus
0.92 times the classification given by
this horizontal line.
So, what that ends up doing is, once you
add these classification
rules up together, you can see that our
classifier works much better now.
We get, to a much better classification
when adding them up, that
gets all of the blue pluses, and all of
the red minuses together.
So in each case, each of our classifiers
was quite simple, was just
a line across the plane, and so, it's
actually quite a naive classifier.
But when you weight them and add them up,
you can
get quite a strong classifier at the end
of the day.
Boosting can be done with any subset of
classifiers.
In other words, you can start with any
sort of weak set of classifiers.
In the previous example, we just used
straight lines to separate the plain.
A very large class is what's called
gradient boosting.
And you can read more about that here.
R has multiple mood, boosting libraries.
So they basically depend on the different
kind of classification functions, and
combination rules.
Gbm package does boosting with trees.
Mboost does model based boost, boosting.
Ada does additive logistic regression
boosting.
And gamBoost does boosting for generalized
additive models.
Most of these are available in the caret
package, so you
can use them directly by using the train
function with caret.
So here we're going to use the wage
example,
to illustrate how you can apply a boosting
algorithm.
So here we're going to load the ISLR
library, and the wage data.
The ggplot2 library, and the caret
library, and then
we're going to, to create a wage data set
that removes the predictor that we care,
or the
variable that we're trying to predict, the
log wage variable.
And we create a training set and a testing
set.
We can then model wage here this wage
variable, as a function of all the
remaining variables.
That's why there's this dot here.
And we can use gbm, which does boosting
with trees, and we use verbose
with a false here, because this will
produces a lot of output when you use.
Method equals gmb, if you dont' say
verbose equals false.
So when we print the model fit, you can
see that there's a different numbers of
trees that
are used, and different interaction
depths, and they're basically
used together, to build a boosted version
of regression trees.
So, here I'm plotting the predicted
results from the testing sets.
So this is the using R model fit.
We're predicting on the test set, versus
the wage variable in the test set.
And you can see we get a real, a
reasonably good
prediction, although there still seems to
be a lot of variability there.
But the basic idea for fitting a boosting
tree a boosted algorithm in general, is to
be,
we take these weak classifiers, and
average them together
with weights, in order to get a better
classifier.
A lot of the information that I have given
in this lecture, can be, be
found in this tutorial, which also has
even more in-depth information if you are
interested.
Here's a little bit more technical
introduction to boosting, from Freund and
Shapire.
And then, here are several more write-ups
about boosting and
random forests these are actually
write-ups from different prizes that
have been won, using a combination of
random forests and
boosting blended together, in order to
achieve maximal prediction accuracy.