So the examples we've talked about so far
in
this class, you often know what the labels
are.
In other words, you're trying to do
supervised classification, you're
trying to predict an outcome that you know
what it is.
But sometimes you don't know the labels
for prediction,
so you have to discover those labels in
advance.
So, one way to do that is to create
clusters from the data that you've
observed, to add names to those clusters
and then build a predictor for those
clusters.
In a new data set, you're going to predict
the cluster and apply
the name that you come up with in the
previous data set.
This adds several levels of difficulty to
the prediction problem.
First of all, creating the clusters is not
a perfectly noiseless process.
Second of all, coming up with the right
names, in
other words interpreting the clusters well
is an incredibly challenging problem.
And if you've taken exploratory data
analysis
in our data science specialization, you'll
understand why.
Building a predictor for the clusters is
basically using the algorithms that we've
learned throughout the course of this
class,
as well as predicting on those clusters.
So I'll just show you a quick example of
how you could do this.
So, if I load the iris data and the
ggplot library, I can then create a
training and test
set for the iris data just like I have
in previous examples, but I could ignore
the species clusters.
So one thing that I could do is I could
perform actually a k-means clustering.
If you remember that k-means clustering
from the
exploratory data analysis section of the
data science specialization.
If you don't, you can look it up on
Wikipedia.
And the basic idea here is to basically
create three different clusters.
So I was telling it to create
three different clusters, ignoring the
species information.
So then what I can do is, I can basically
assign to those clusters different colors.
And so here I've plotted those three
different clusters that are created by
performing
this k-means clustering, so there's a
cluster
here, a cluster here and a cluster here.
Those clusters actually are relatively
close to the clusters
you would get if you used the species
labels
themselves, but that's not a typical
outcome, often it's
very hard to label the clusters that you
get.
So in this case, I can make a table of the
cluster
versus species, and I can see that cluster
2 corresponds to this species.
Cluster 3 corresponds to this species and
cluster 1 corresponds to this species.
So in general, I wouldn't know what those
species names were, and
I would have to come up with names for
each of my clusters.
And then I can fit a model that relates
the cluster variable that I've just
created, to all the predictor variables
and I could do it in the training set.
In this case, I am doing it with a
classification tree.
I can then do a prediction in a, a
training set,
and I can see that I do a reasonably good
job
of predicting this cluster and this
cluster but cluster 1 and
cluster 3 sometimes get mix, mixed up in
my prediction model.
That's because I have both error or
variation in
my prediction building and error and
variation in my
cluster building, so it ends up being a
quite
a challenging problem to do, unsupervised
prediction in this way.
I can then apply it on the test data set.
So if I predict on the test data set, in
general I wouldn't
know what the labels are, but here I'm
showing what the labels are.
So, here I'm predicting on a new data set
and making a table versus the actual known
species.
And so I can see this actually does quite
a reasonable
job here of predicting the different
species into different clustered labels.
In general, this is quite a hard problem,
so care must be taken in the labeling the
clusters, and performing the unsupervised
analysis and understanding how that works.
The cl_predict function in the clue
package provides similar functionality to
what I've
just described here, but in general it
makes a little bit more sense
to sort of build your own
approach if you're doing unsupervised
prediction because
you really need to think carefully about
how you're going to define the clusters.
Be very wary of over interpretation of
this type of clusters.
This is in fact an exploratory technique.
And so the clusters may change depend on
the way that you sample the data.
This is actually one basic approach to
building things like recommendation
engines, where you
identify clusters of people that have
similar
tastes and assign their tastes to new
individuals.
You can read more about unsupervised
prediction in the
elements of statistical learning and
introduction to statistical learning.