This lecture is about combining
predictors,
it's sometimes called ensembling methods
in learning.
And so the key idea here is that you can
combine classifiers
by averaging or voting and these can be
classifiers that are very different.
So for example you can combine a boosting
classifier
with a random forest with a linear
regression model.
In general combining classifiers together
improves accuracy
and it can also reduce interpretive
abilities you
have to be really careful the gain that
you get is worth the loss on
interperatibility.
Boosting, bagging and random floor,
they're all basically variance
on this theme that you can average
different classifiers together.
But those are all examples where it's the
same kind of classifiers being averaged in
every case.
So as an example of how successful this
can be, the Netflix prize
was a million dollar prize that was
basically major prediction competition
that was run.
And so the team that ended up wining
was actually a blended combination of 107
different.
Machine learning algorithms combined
together in order
to get the best score in this example.
The Heritage Health prize was also won by
methods that
were ensembling for multiple different
regression models and machine learning
methods.
And so this was these are both of the
links to the
first progress prizes for the two teams
that were in the lead.
The Heritage Health prize was a $3 million
prize.
It was designed to try to predict whether
people would
go back to the hospital based on their
hospitalization record.
So the basic intuition here, you can think
of as a majority vote.
So suppose we have five completely
independent classifiers.
If the accuracy at 70% for each
classifier, then we
can think that, the accuracy for majority
vote would be.
10 times the majority vote being right for
three out of the five classifiers,
for four out of the five classifiers, or
for all five classifiers.
And so it turns out that would be 83.7%
majority vote accuracy.
With 101 independent classifiers you get
99.9% majority vote accuracy.
So some approaches for combining
classifiers
basically use, one approach is using
similar
classifiers and combining them together
using
something like bagging, boosting, or
random forests.
Another approach is to combine different
classifiers using model stacking or model
ensembling,
and we're going to talk a little bit about
model stacking in this lecture.
So, here's an example with the wage data.
So, where going to, build the wage data
set
and we're going to leave out the log wage
variable.
Since we're trying to predict wage, log
wage would be a very good predictor.
And, we build the, validation set here.
And, we also build a training set and a
test set.
So, I've separated it into three different
data sets here.
And that, you'll see the importance of
that in just a minute.
So the training set is the largest of the
data sets.
It has a 100, 1,474 examples.
The test set has 628 and the validation
set has 898 samples in it.
We, then, in the training set, build.
In this case, I'm using a GLM.
So this is a linear model.
And I'm building it in the, training data.
And I'm basically predicting wage using
all the other variables.
I'm also going to build a separate model,
also in the training data.
And I'm going to, here, use method equals
random forest.
And so I'm fitting two different
prediction models to the same data set.
I can then plot those predictions versus
each other so this is the predictions
here.
Pred1 is the predictions from the linear
model,
and pred2 are the predictions from the
random forest.
And you can see that they, they're close
to
each other, but they don't actually agree
with each other.
And, neither of them perfectly correlates
with the wage variable,
which is the color of the dots in this
particular picture.
So then what we can do is fit a model that
combines the predictors.
So, I basically build a new data set
consisting of
the predictions from model one and the
predictions from model two.
And then what I can do is I can create a
wage
variable, which is the, the, on the test
data set, the wage variable.
Then I can fit a new model, which
relates this wage variable, to the two
predictions.
So now, instead of just fitting a model
that relates the co-variants
to the outcome, I've fit two separate
prediction models for the outcome.
And now now I'm fitting a regression model
ratin,
relating the outcome to the predictions
for those two models.
And then I can predict from the combined
data set on new samples.
So, I can look at the how well I do on the
test set
and so I can see that for example on the
test set the first predictor.
Has an error of 827.1 and the second
predictor has an error of 866,
whereas the combined predictor has an
error that's lower, 813.9.
And I also want to try it out on the
validation set because remember
I use the test set to try to blend the two
models together.
So, I fit a model on the test set, so
that's not a good representation of the
out of sample error.
So, now I basically create a prediction of
my first model on the
validation set and a prediction of my
second model on the validation set.
I then create a data frame that contains
those two predictions.
And now I predict using my model, my
combined
model, on the predictions in the
validation data set.
So the covariance being passed in the
model
are the predictions from the two different
models.
So here I can see the error from model one
if I used it by itself would be 1003.
The error for my second model would be
1068.
And the combined model has a lower error
even on the validation data set.
So stacking models in this way can re,
improve accuracy
by blending different models, the
strengths of different models together.
Even simple blending like I've talked
about here
can be really useful and can improve
accuracy.
The typical model blending for mul, binary
multiclass data involves building
an odd number of models, predicting the
outcome with each model.
And then, assigning the ultimate class
label based on majority vote.
This can get dramatically more
complicated, I, I found
a caret package ensemble that, ensembles
some of the
caret models together, but it's a little
bit in
development, so I'd say use at your own
risk.
You can also read more about ensemble
learning here
at the Wikipedia page that I've linked to
here.
One important point to keep in mind when
doing model
ensembling is that this can lead to
increases in computational complexity.
So it turns out that even though Netflix
paid
a million dollars to the team that won the
prize.
The solution, the Netflix millionaire
dollar solution was never actually
implemented.
Because it was too computational intensive
to apply to specific data sets.
So, recall from the earliest lectures in
this class that there are trade offs in
scalability versus accuracy that you have
to
pay attention to when building these
prediction models.