This lecture is about Regularized
regression.
We learned about linear regression and
generalized linear regression previously.
For the basic idea here is to fit one of
these regression models.
And then, penalize or shrink the large
coefficients corresponding with some of
the predictor variables.
The reason why we might do this is
because it might help with the bias
variance tradeoff.
If certain variables are highly
coordinated with each other.
For example, you might not want to include
them both in
the linear regression model as they will
have a very high variance.
Which might slightly, leaving one of them
out, might slightly bias your model.
In other words, you might lose a little
bit of prediction capability, but
you'll save a lot on the variants
and therefore improve your prediction to
error.
It can also help with model selection, in
certain cases for regular organization
techniques like the lasso.
It may be computationally demanding on
large data sets.
And in general, it appears that it does
not perform as quite as
well as random forests or boosting, when
applied to prediction in the wild.
For example, in cattle competitions.
So as a motivating example, suppose we fit
a very simple regression model.
So there's an outcome Y.
And we're trying to predict it with two
covariants, x1 and x2.
So we have an intercept terms so this is a
constant.
Plus another constant times x1 plus
another constant times x2.
>> So assume that x1 and x2 are nearly
perfectly correlated.
In other words they're almost exactly the
same variable.
The word for this in linear modeling is
often called co-linear.
You can then approximate this more
complicated model.
By saying, well, what if we just include
only X1
and multiply it by both the coefficients
for X1 and X2.
It won't be exactly right, because X1 and
X2 aren't exactly the same variable.
But it will be very close to right, if X1
and X2 are very similar to each other.
The result may be that you still get a
very good estimate of y.
The same, almost as good as you would've
got by including both predictors in the
model.
And you, it will be a little bit biased,
because we chose to leave one of the
predictors out.
But we may reduce the variance if those
two variables are highly correlated with
each other.
So here's an example, with, prostate
cancer data
set and the elements of statistical
learning library.
We can load the prostate data and look at
that data set it has, 97 observations on
ten variables.
And so one thing that we might want to be
able
to do is make a prediction about, prostate
cancer, PSA.
Based on a large number of predictors in
the data set.
And so this is a very typical of
what happens when you build these models
in practice.
So suppose we predict with all possible
combinations of predictor variables.
We go to the linear regression model.
For the outcome where we build one
regression model for every possible
combination of vectors.
Then we can see as the number of
predictors increases from
left to right here, the training set error
always goes down.
It has to down.
As you include more predictors, the
training set error will always decrease.
But this is a typical pattern of what you
observe with real data.
That the test set data on the other hand,
as the number
of predictors increases, the test set
error goes down, which is good.
But then eventually it hits a plateau, and
it starts to go back up again.
This is because we're overfitting the data
in the training set, and
eventually, we may not want to include so
many predictors in our model.
This is an incredibly common pattern.
Basically any measure of model complexity
on the x-axis versus
the expected Residual Sum of Squares of
the predicted error.
You can see that in the training set
almost always
the error goes monotonically down, in
other words, as you build.
More and more complicated models, the
training error will always decrease.
But on a testing set, the error will
decrease for a while, eventual hit a
minimum.
And then, start to increase again as the
model gets too complex and over fits the
data.
So, in general, what the best approach
might be when, when you
have enough data and you have enough
computation time to split samples.
So the idea is divide your data into
training, test, and validation sets.
You treat the validation set as the test
data and you train every possible
competing model.
So all possible subsets on the training
data.
And pick the best, the one that works best
on the validation data set.
But now that we've used the validation set
for training, we
need to assess the error rate on a
completely independent set.
So we appropriately assess this
performance by applying our
prediction to the new data in the test
set.
Sometimes you may re, re-perform the
splitting and analysis several times.
In order to get a better average estimate
of
what the out of sample error rate will be.
But there are two common problems with
this
approach, one is that there might be
limited data.
Here we're breaking the data set up into
three different data sets.
It might not be possible to get a very
good model fit when we split the data that
finely.
Second, is computational complexity.
If you're trying all possible subsets of
models it can be very
complicated, especially if you have a lot,
a lot of predictor variables.
So another approach is to try to decompose
the prediction error.
And see if there's another way that we can
work directly get
at including only the variable that need
to be included in the model.
So if we assume that the variable y can be
predicted as a function of x, plus some
error term,.
Then the expected prediction error is the
expected difference
between the outcome and the prediction of
the outcome squared.
And so, f-hat lambda here is the estimate
from the training set.
Using a particular set of tuning
parameters lambda.
Then if we look at a new point.
So we bring in a new data point and we
look at the distance between our var, our
observed outcome.
And the prediction on the new data point.
That can be decomposed after some algebra
into irreducible error.
This sigma squared.
The bias, so this is the difference
between our expected
prediction and the truth, and the variance
of our estimate.
So the question, so whenever you're
building a prediction
model the goal is to reduce this overall
quantity.
So this is basically the expected.
Mean squared error between our our outcome
and our prediction.
And so, the irreducible error can't
usually be reduced.
It's value that's just part of the data
you're collecting.
But you can trade off bias and variance.
And that's what the idea behind
regularized regression does.
So another issue for high dimensional
data, is suppose I'm just showing you
a simple example of what happens when you
have a lot of predictors.
So here I'm sub setting just a small
subset of the prostate
data, so imagine that I only had five
observations in my training set.
It has more than five predictor variables.
So I fit a linear model relating
the outcome to all of these predictor
variables.
And there are more than five.
Then some of them will get estimates.
But some of them will be NA.
In other words, r won't be able to
estimate
them because you have more predictors than
you have samples.
And, so you have, design matrix that
cannot be inverted.
So here we have one approach to dealing
with this problem is
we can, and the other problem of trying to
select our model.
Is we could take this model that we have,
and assume that it has a linear form, like
this.
So assume that it's a linear regression
model, like we've talked about before.
And then constrain only the lambda of the
coefficients to be non-zero.
And then the question is, after we pick
lambda, so suppose there are only three
non-zero coefficients.
Then we have to try all the possible
combinations of
three coefficients that are non-zero, and
then fit the best model.
So that's still computationally quite
demanding.
So another approach is to use regularized
regression.
So if the beta j, so if our coefficients
that we're fitting in the linear model are
unconstrained.
In other words, we don't make, we don't
claim that they have any particular form.
They may explode if they're very, if you
have
very highly correlated variables that
you're using for prediction.
And so, they can be susceptible to high
variance.
And the high variance means that you'll
get predictions that aren't as accurate.
So to control the variance we might
regularize, or shrink the coefficients.
So, remember that, we, what we might
want to minimize, is some
kind of distance between our outcome that
we have and our linear model.
So here, this is the distance between the
outcome and the linear model fit squared.
That's the residual sum of squares.
Then you might also add a penalty term
here.
That says, the penalty will basically say:
if the beta
coefficients are too big, it will shrink
them back down.
So the penalty is usually used to reduce
complexity.
It can be used to reduce variance.
And it can respect some of the structure
in the
problem if you set the penalty up in the
right way.
The first approach that was used in this
sort of penalized regression is to fit the
regression model.
Here again, we're penalizing a distance
between
our outcome y and our regression model
here.
And then we also have a term here.
That is lambda times the sum of the beta
j's squared.
So, what does this mean?
If the beta j's squares are really big
then this term will
get too big, so we'll get, we won't get a
very good fit.
This whole quantity will end up being very
big, so
it basically requires that some of the
beta j's be small.
It's actually equivalent to solving this
problem where we're looking for
the smallest sum of squared here and sum
of squared differences here.
Subject to a particular constraint that,
the sum
of squared beta j's is less than s.
So the idea here is that the inclusion of
this lambda coefficient may also even make
the problem non-singular.
Even when the x transpose x is not
invertible.
In other words, in that model fit where we
have more predictors
than we do observations the ridge
regression model can still be fit.
So this is what the coefficient path looks
like.
So what do I mean by coefficient path.
For every different choice of lamda, that
penalized
regression problem on the previous page,
as gambit increases.
That means that we penalize the big datas
more and more.
So we start off with the betas being equal
to
a certain of values here when lambda's
equal to 0.
That's just a standard linear with
regression values.
And as you increase lambda, all of the
coefficients get closer to 0.
Because we're penalizing the coefficients,
and make, and making them smaller.
So the tuning parameter lambda controls
the size of the control coefficients.
Lambda controls the amount of
regularization.
As lambda get's closer and closer to 0, we
basically go back to
the least square solution which is what
you get from a standard linear model.
And as lambda goes to infinitely we
basically,
so in other words as lambda get's really
big.
It penalizes the coefficients a lot, and
so all of the
conditioned coefficients go toward 0 as
the, tuning parameter gets really big.
So taking that parameter can be done with
cross-validation or
other techniques to try to pick the
optimal tuning parameter.
That trades off bias for variance.
A similar approach can be done with a
slight change of penalty.
So again, here we might be solving the
problem again, this lees squares problem.
This is the standard trying to identify
the beta
values that make this distance to the
outcome smallest.
And here we can constrain it subject to
the sum of
the absolute value of the beta j's being
less than sum value.
You can also write that as a penalized
regression of this
form, so we're trying to solve this
penalized sum of squares.
So for ortho normal design matrix which
you
can, see on Wikipedia or the normal design
matrix.
The idea is that this actually has a
closed form solution.
And the closed form solution is basically,
take the absolute
value of the beta j and subtract off a
gamma value.
And take only the positive part.
In other words if gamma is bigger than
your least
squared beta hat j then this will be a
negative number.
And you're taking only the positive part
so you set it equal to 0.
So if it's a positive though if this
absolute
beta hat j is bigger than, the gamma
value.
Then this whole number will be a smaller
positive number.
It will be shrunk by the amount gamma.
And then, we multiply it by the sign of
the original coefficient.
So what is this doing?
Its basically saying the lasso shrinks all
of the
coefficients and set some of them to
exactly 0.
And some people like this approach because
it both shrinks coefficients.
And by setting something exactly to 0
it performs model selection for you in
advance.
There are really good set of lecture notes
from Hector Corrada Bravo.
That you can find here at this link.
He also has a very nice list on the large
number of penalized regression models.
And in the Elements of Statistical
Learning book
covers this penalized regression idea a
quite extensive detail.
If you want to follow along there.
In caret, if you want to fit these models,
you can set the
method to ridge, lasso or relaxo to
fit different kinds of penalized
regression models.