This lecture is about forecasting, which
is
a very specific kind of prediction
problem.
And it's typically applied to things like
time series data.
So, for example, this is the stock of
information for
Google on the NASDAQ, and so is this
symbol GOOG.
And you can see over time that there's a
price for this stock and it goes up and
down.
So this introduces some very specific
kinds of dependent structure and
some additional challenges that must be
taken into account when performing
prediction.
And so, first of all, the data are
dependent over time, and so, that alone
makes prediction a little bit more
challenging
than it is when you have independent
examples.
There's also some specific pattern types
that should be paid attention to.
Trends, such as long term increases or
decreases, seasonal
patterns are very common in this kind of
data.
For example, seasonal patterns over weeks,
months, years, etc.
Cycles, patterns that rise and fall
periodically over
a period that's longer than a year, for
example.
Here, the subsampling and the training and
test can be a little bit
more complicated because you can't just
randomly assign samples into training and
test.
You have to take advantage of the fact
that there's actually specific
times that are being sampled and that
points are dependent in time.
Similar issues arise in predictions of
spatial den, spatial data.
For example, there's dependency between
nearby observations and there may
be location-specific effects that have to
be modeled when doing prediction.
Typically, the goal here is to predict one
or
more observations into the future and all
standard prediction
algorithms can be used, but you have to be
a little bit cautious about how you use
them.
So, one thing to be aware of is
that you have to be careful of spurious
correlations.
So, time series can often be correlate for
reasons that
do not make them good for predicting one
from the other.
So, if you look at, you can go to Google
Correlate to
correlate different words over time, the
frequency of different words over time.
And so, for example, here you can see a
correlation between the
Google stock price, shown in blue, and
solitaire network, which is in red.
And so, those don't necessarily have
anything to do with each other at
all, but they have a very high
correlation, and you might think you might
be able to predict one from the other,
even though in the future,
they might diverge substantially because
they aren't
necessarily related to each other at all.
It's also very common in geographic
analysis.
This is actually a cartoon from xkcd
that shows that heat maps particularly
population-based
heat maps had very similar shapes because
of the place where many people live.
So for example, the users of a particular
site or the subscribers
to a particular magazine or the consume,
consumers of a particular type of
website may all appear in the very similar
places because the highest density
in population in the United States is over
here on the Eastern seaboard.
And so, you see very similar heat maps of
a
large number of individuals at all of
those different places.
You should also beware of extrapolation.
So this is a kind of a funny example that
shows what happens
if you extrapolate time series out without
being careful about what could happen.
So this shows on a long scale the winning
time of a
large number of oh sorry, of races that
occurred at the Olympics.
The blue times are men and the red times
are
women, and these authors of this paper
extrapolated out into
the future and said that in 2156 that
would be
when women would run faster than men in
the sprint.
And while we don't know when that, when or
when that may or may not
occur, one thing that was pointed out is
that this kind of extrapolation is very
dangerous.
Eventually at some time in the future,
both men and women
will be predicted to run negative times
for the 100 meters.
And so, you have to be very careful
about how far out you extrapolate from
your data.
So, I'm going to show a quick example of
some
forecasting using the quantmod package and
some Google data.
So, if I load this quantmod package and I
can, I
can load in a bunch of data from the
Google stock symbol.
And I can get it from the Google finance
data set.
And so if I look at this Google variable,
I get the open, high,
low, close, and volume information for a
particular Google stock from
the 1st of January, 2008 to December 31st,
2013.
So I can summarize this monthly and store
it as a time series.
So I can use the two monthly variable or
function to convert that to a monthly time
series.
And I can just take the opening
information, and then I
can create a time series object using the
ts function in R.
And if I plot that, I can see here's the
monthly opening prices for Google over a
period of seven years.
So, an example time series decomposition
would decompose this
time series into a trend, any kind of
consistent
pattern, a seasonal pattern over time, and
cyclic patterns
where the data rises and falls over non
fixed periods.
And so, one way that we can do this is
with the decompose function in R.
So if I decompose this in an additive way,
then I can see that there's
a trend variable that appears to be an
upward trend of the Google stock price.
There also appears to be a seasonal
pattern, as well as
a more of a random cyclical pattern in the
data set.
So this is decomposing this series here
into a
series of different types of patterns in
the data.
So here for training and test sets, I have
to
build training and test sets that have
consecutive time points.
So here I am building a training set that
starts
at time point 1 and ends at time point 5.
And then a test set that is the next
consecutive sets of points after that.
So that way, I can always build a training
set and apply it to a test set
that have consecutive time points that
show the same
sort of trends that I've observed in my
data.
So there's a couple different ways for
doing forecasting.
One is to do a simple moving average,
which in another words, it
basically averages up all of the values
of, for a particular time point.
And the prediction will be the average of
the previous time points out to a
particular time.
You can also do exponential smoothing.
In other words, basically we weight
near-by time points as higher
values or by more heavily than time points
that are farther away.
So there's a large number of different
classes of smoothing models that you can
choose.
And for exponential smoothing, you can get
an, you can fit a model where you have a
different choices for the different types
of trends that you might want to fit.
And then when you forecast, you can get
a prediction that comes out of your
forecasting model.
And you can also get sort of a prediction
bounds for
what are the possible values that you
could get from that prediction.
And you can get the accuracy using this
accuracy function,
so you can basically get the accuracy of
your forecast using
your test set, and it will give you root
mean square
to error and other metrics that are more
appropriate for forecasting.
I've obviously gone through this very fast
and so, if you want more
information, there's actually an entire
field
dedicated to forecasting and time series
prediction.
And I would highly recommend Rob Hyndman's
Forecasting: principles and practice.
This is a free book that's online and it's
really, really good, and
has a lot of information about how to get
started at, in forecasting.
So the cautions are to be wary of spurious
correlations.
Be very careful about how far you predic,
predict out into the future
with express, extrapolation, and be wary
of dependencies like seasonal effects over
time.
If you would like information on you, for
financial prediction and financial
forecasting, the quantmod and quandl
packages
are also very useful in that area.